<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned and necessary argument to prove that each subject hath a propriety in his goods shewing also the extent of the kings prerogative in impositions upon the goods of merchants exported and imported out of and into this kingdome : together with a remonstrance presented to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty by the Honourable House of Commons in the Parliament holden anno dom. 1610, annoq[ue] regis Jacobi, 7 / by a late learned judge of this kingdome.</title>
            <author>Whitelocke, James, Sir, 1570-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1995aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875726</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152499</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96414)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152499)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2299:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned and necessary argument to prove that each subject hath a propriety in his goods shewing also the extent of the kings prerogative in impositions upon the goods of merchants exported and imported out of and into this kingdome : together with a remonstrance presented to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty by the Honourable House of Commons in the Parliament holden anno dom. 1610, annoq[ue] regis Jacobi, 7 / by a late learned judge of this kingdome.</title>
                  <author>Whitelocke, James, Sir, 1570-1632.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 66, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Bishop for Iohn Burroughes and are to be sold by Richard Hassell ... in Bristoll,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625.</term>
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Constitutional law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tariff --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152499:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A learned and neceſſary ARGUMENT To prove that each Subject hath a Propriety in his Goods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewing alſo</hi> The extent of the Kings Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative in Impoſitions upon the Goods of Merchants exported and imported, out of and into this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Together with a Remonſtrance preſented to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, by the honourable Houſe of Commons, in the Parliament holden <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1610. <hi>Anno<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Regis Jacobi,</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>By a late learned Judge of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Richard Biſhop</hi> for <hi>Iohn Burroughes,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Haſſell</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152499:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152499:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>THis excellent Treatiſe of the no leſſe worthy Author, happily falling into my hands, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly thought it my duty to make that publick, which had given ſo much uſefull ſatisfaction to many learned, and judicious, in private; remembring that ancient Adage, <hi>Bonum quò communius, eò prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope it is needleſſe to commend either the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Author deceaſed, the Treatiſe, its uſe, or ſtile; ſince the Authority by which it is publiſhed, is a ſufficient argument of their knowne worth.</p>
            <p>If thou kindly accept his good meaning, whoſe only ayme in the publiſhing hereof was the Common good, it will be an encouragement to him (and others) to preſent to thy view, what may hereafter fall into his hands worthy thy further peruſall.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine;</hi> I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:152499:3"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>20. <hi>Maii,</hi> 1641.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>AT a Committee appointed by the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe of Commons, for examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Books, and of the licencing, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is ordered, that this Treatiſe be publiſhed in Print.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir EDWARD DERING, Knight and Baronet.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152499:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Remonſtrance delivered to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie in writing, after the inhibition given by him to the Commons houſe of Parliament, aſwell by word of mouth, as by letters, not to proceed in the examining his right to impoſe without aſſent of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt gracious Soveraigne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas we your Majeſties moſt humble Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the Commons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have received firſt by meſſage, and ſince by ſpeech from your Majeſty a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of reſtraint, from debating in Parliament your Majeſties right of impoſing upon your ſubjects goods exported, or imported out of, or into this Realme: yet allowing us to examine the greivance of theſe impoſitions in regard of quantity, time, and other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of diſproportion thereto incident: We your ſaid humble Subjects nothing doubting but that your Majeſty had no intent by that Command to infringe, the ancient and fundamentall right of the Liberty of Parliament in point of exact diſcuſſing of all matters concerning them, and their poſſeſsions, goods and rights whatſoever, which yet we cannot but conceive to be done in effect by this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152499:4"/>doe with all humble duty make this Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance unto your Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Friſt, we hold it an ancient, generall, and undoubted right of Parliament, to debate freely all matters which doe properly concerne the ſubject, and his right or eſtate; which freedome of debate being once fore-cloſed, the eſſence of the liberty of Parliament is withall diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>And whereas in this caſe the ſubjects right on the one fide, and your Majeſties prerogative on the other, cannot poſſibly bee ſevered in debate of either; Wee alledge that your Majeſties Prerogatives of that kinde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning directly the ſubjects right and intereſt, are daily handled and diſcuſſed in all Courts at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, and have been ever freely debated upon all fit occaſions, both in this and all other former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, without reſtraint; which being forbidden, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the ſubject, either to know, or to maintaine his right and propriety to his owne lands and goods, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo juſt and manifeſt.</p>
            <p>It may further pleaſe your moſt excellent Majeſty to underſtand, that wee have no minde to impugne, but a deſire to informe our ſelves of your Highneſſe Proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in that point, which (if ever) is now moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to be knowne; and though it were to no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, yet to ſatisfie the generalitie of your Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who finding themſelves much grieved by theſe new impoſitions, doe languiſh in much ſorrow and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort.</p>
            <p>Theſe reaſons (Dread Soveraigne) being the proper reaſons of Parliament, doe plead for the upholding of this our ancient Right and Libertie. Howbeit ſeeing it hath pleaſed your Majeſtie to inſiſt upon that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Exchequer, as being direction ſufficient for us without further examination: Upon great deſire of leaving your Majeſty unſatisfied in no one point of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152499:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and proceedings, We profeſſe touching that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that wee neither doe nor will take upon us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe it; but our deſire is to know the reaſons whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame was grounded; and the rather for that a generall conceit is had, That the reaſons of that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may bee extended much further, even to the utter ruine of the ancient liberty of this Kingdome, and of your ſubjects right of proprietie to their goods and lands</p>
            <p>Then for the judgement it ſelfe, being the firſt and laſt that ever was given in that kind (for ought appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto us,) and being onely in one Caſe, and againſt one man, it can binde in law no other, but that perſon; and is alſo reverſible by Writ of errour granted hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by act of Parliament. And neither be nor any other ſubject is debarred by it, from trying his right in the ſame or like caſe, in any of your Majeſties Courts of Record at Weſtminſter.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we nothing doubt, but our intended proceeding in a full examination of the right, nature, and meaſure of theſe new impoſitions (if this reſtraint had not come betweene) ſhould have been ſo orderly and ſo mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately carried and employed to the manifold neceſſities of theſe times, and given your Majeſty ſo true a view of the ſtate and right of your ſubjects, that it would have been much to your Majeſties content and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (which wee moſt deſire,) and removed all cauſes of feares and jealouſies from the loyall hearts of your Subjects, which is (as it ought to bee) our carefull endeavour: whereas contrariwiſe in that other way di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by your Majeſtie, wee cannot ſafely proceede without concluding for ever the right of the ſubject, which without due examination thereof wee may not doe.</p>
            <p>Wee therefore your loyall and dutifull Commons, not ſwarving from the approved ſteps of our Anceſtours, moſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152499:5"/>humbly and inſtantly beſeech your gracious Majeſtie, that without offence to the ſame, we may, according to the undoubted right and liberty of Parliament, proceede in our intended courſe of a full examination of theſe new impoſitions: That ſo wee may cheerefully paſſe on to your Majeſties buſineſſe, from which this ſtop hath by diverſion ſo long withheld us. And we your Majeſties moſt humble, faithfull, and loyall Subjects, ſhall ever (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our bounden duty) pray for your Majeſties long and happy reigne over us.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152499:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The queſtion is, whether the King, without aſſent of Parliament, may ſet impoſitions upon the wares, and goods of merchants exported, and imported, out, of, and into, this Realme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree things have been debated in this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that have much concerned the right of our whole Nation, of which every one of them hath exceeded the other by a gradation in waight and moment.</p>
            <p>The firſt, was the change of our name, which was a point of honour,
<note place="margin">The name of Britaine not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</note> wherein we ſhewed our ſelves not willing to leave that name, by which our anceſtors made our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion famous: yet have we loſt it, ſaving onely in thoſe caſes where our ancient and faithfull protector, the Common Law doth reteine it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was the union; a queſtion of greater moment, for that concerned the freehold of our whole Nation, not in ſo high a point as having, or not having; but in point of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; participation, that is, whether we ſhould enjoy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and liberties of the kingdome our ſelves onely as we and our anceſtors have done, or admit our neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to have equall right in them, and ſo make our owne part the leſſe, by how much the greater number ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom the Diviſion was to be made.
<note place="margin">Coke <hi>li</hi> 7. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s caſe.</note> This was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged againſt us both Legally and ſolemnly, and therefore in that we reſt, hoping of that effect of this judgement which we read of in the Poet:
<note place="margin">Virgil Aeneid. <hi>l.</hi> 1, Dido's <hi>ſpeech to</hi> Aeneas.</note>
               <q>Tros Tyriuſque mihi nullo diſcrimine habetur.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The third is the queſtion now in hand, which exceedeth the other two in importance and conſequence, concerning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152499:6"/>the whole kingdome, for it is a queſtion of our very eſſence, not what we ſhall be called, nor how we ſhall divide that we have, but whether we ſhall have any thing or nothing: for if there be a right in the King to alter the property of that which is ours without our conſents, we are but te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants at his will of that which we have. If it be in the King and Parliament: Then have we propertie, and are tenants at our owne will: for that which is done in Parliament is done by all our wills and conſents. And this is the very ſtate of the queſtion which is propoſed, that is, whether the King may impoſe without conſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Impoſitions are of two natures, <hi>Forreine</hi> and <hi>Inteſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inteſtine be thoſe, which are raiſed within our land in the commerce and dealing that is at home within our ſelves, and may aſwell for that reaſon be ſo called, as for that <hi>veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur inteſtinis Reipublicae,</hi> They are fed, and nouriſhed with the conſuming and waſting of the entralls of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. Againſt theſe I neede not to ſpeake; for the Kings learned Counſell have with great honour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in full Councell acknowledged them to be againſt the law.</p>
            <p>Therefore I will apply my ſelfe to ſpeake of impoſitions forreine, being the ſingle queſtion now in hand, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained on the Kings behalfe with great art and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
            <p>The inconvenience of theſe impoſitions to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that is, how hurtfull they are to the Merchants, in impoveriſhing them in their eſtates; to the King in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of his revenues by decay of traffique, and to the whole people in making all commodities exceſſive deare, is confeſſed by all; and therefore need no debate. The point of right is now only in queſtion, and of that I will ſpeak with conſcience and integrity, rather deſirous that the truth may be knowne, and right be done, than that the opinion of my ſelfe, or any other may prevaile.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this queſtion was given by the book of rates lately ſet out, affronted with the copy of Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, dated <hi>July</hi> 28.6. <hi>Jac.</hi> In which book, beſides the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152499:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>rates, is ſet downe upon every kinde of merchandiſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and imported, for the true anſwering of ſubſidy to the King, according to the Statute of tonnage and poundage. In the firſt yeare of his reigne there is an addition of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions upon all thoſe kinde of wares, which within the book are expreſſed, and the rate of the impoſition as high and in ſome caſes higher, than the rate of the ſubſidy: And this declared to be by authority of thoſe Letters Patents. Heare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon conſidering with my ſelfe, that heretofore the ſetting on of one only impoſition without aſſent of Parliament, upon ſome one kinde of merchandiſe, and that for a ſmall time, and upon urgent neceſſity of actuall warre, did ſo affect our whole Nation, and eſpecially the great Councell of the Parliament, being the repreſentative body of the whole Common-wealth; that neither the ſunne did ſhine, nor the rivers runne their courſes, untill it was taken off by the publick judgement of the whole State. I thought it concerned me, and other members of that Councell, that were no leſſe truſted for our countreys, than thoſe in former times, and have their actions to guide and direct us, to have the ſame care they had in preſerving the right, and liberties of the people, having now more cauſe then they had, for that the impoſitions, now ſet on without aſſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are not upon one or two ſpeciall kindes of goods, but almoſt indefinite upon all, and doe extend to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of many hundreds, as appeareth by that printed book of rates, and are ſet in charge upon the whole kingdome, as an inheritance to continue to the King, his heires and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours for ever: which limitation of eſtate in matter of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions was never heard of, nor read of before as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
            <p>The inducements expreſſed in theſe Letters Patents are much upon point of State, and with reference to the rights and practiſe of forraine princes; For this I will not take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to enter into the conſideration of ſuch great miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of policie, and governement, but will only put you in minde of that I obſerve out of <hi>Tit.
<note place="margin">Tit. Liu. 8.</note> Livius</hi> the Romane <hi>Hi ſtoriographer: Omnem divini, humanique moris memoriam
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152499:7"/>abolemus, cum novâ peregrinâque patriis, &amp; priſcis praefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To that which hath been ſpoken for the Kings Prerogative, I will give anſwer to ſo much of it, as I may conveniently in my paſſage through this debate: wherein I will principally endevour to give ſatisfaction to ſuch new objections, as were made by the worthie and learned Counſelor of the King that ſpake laſt, in maintenance of his Maieſties Prerogative.</p>
            <p>The caſe in termes is this:
<note place="margin">Pat. Iuly 28. <hi>Iac.</hi> 6.</note> The King by his Letters Patents before recited hath ordained, willed, and commanded that theſe new impoſitions contained in that booke of rates ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be for ever hereafter payd unto him, his heires, and ſucceſſors, upon paine of his diſpleaſure: Herevpon the queſtion ariſeth whether by this Edict and Ordinance ſo made by the King himſelfe, by his Letters Patents of his owne will and power abſolute, without aſſent of Parliament, he be ſo lawfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to that he doth impoſe, as that thereby he doth alter the property of his ſubjects goods, and is enabled to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver theſe impoſitions by courſe of Law.</p>
            <p>I think he cannot; and I ground my opinion upon theſe foure reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is againſt the naturall frame and conſtitution of the policie of this kingdome, which is <hi>jus publicum regni,</hi> and ſo ſubverteth the fundamentall Law of the Realme, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth a new forme of ſtate and government.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is againſt the municipall Law of the Land, which is <hi>jus priuatum,</hi> the Law of property and of private right.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is againſt Divers ſtatutes made to reſtraine our King in this point.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It is againſt the practice and action of our Common wealth, <hi>contra morem majorum;</hi> and this is the modeſteſt rule to limit both Kings Prerogatives, and ſubiects liberties.</p>
            <p>Upon the firſt, and fourth of theſe foure principall grounds I will more inſiſt then upon the ſecond and third, both for that in their owne nature they are a more proper matter for a Councell of State, to the judgement of which I apply my diſcourſe (and they have not beene enforced by others:) As alſo for that the other two (as more fit for a barre, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152499:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Courts of ordinary juſtice) have by ſome profeſſors of the Law beene already moſt learnedly, and exquiſitely diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>For the firſt: it will be admitted for a rule, and ground of State, that in every Common-wealth and government, there be ſome rights of Sovereignty, <hi>jura Majeſtatis,</hi> which regularly, and of common right doe belong to the Soveraign power of that State; unleſſe Cuſtome, or the proviſionall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of that State doe otherwiſe diſpoſe of them; which Soveraigne power is <hi>poteſtas ſuprema,</hi> a power that can controule all other powers, and cannot be controuled but by it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>It will not be denied, that the power of impoſing hath ſo great a truſt in it, by reaſon of the miſchiefes may grow to the Common-wealth by the abuſes of it, that it hath ever beene ranked among thoſe rights of Soveraigne power.</p>
            <p>Then is there no further queſtion to be made, but to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, where the Soveraigne power is in this Kingdome; for there is the right of impoſition?</p>
            <p>The Soveraigne power is agreed to be in the King: but in the King is a twofold power; the one in Parliament, as he is aſſiſted with the conſent of the whole State; the other out of Parliament, as he is ſole, and ſingular guided merely by his owne will. And if of theſe two powers in the King one is greater than the other, and can direct and controule the other; that is, <hi>Suprema Poteſtas,</hi> the Soveraigne Power, and the other is <hi>ſubordinata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will then be eaſily proved, that the power of the King in Parliament is greater than his power out of Parliament, and doth rule and controule it; for if the King make a grant by his Letters Patents out of Parliament, it bindeth him and his ſucceſſours, he cannot revoke it, nor any of his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours; But by his power in Parliament he may defeate and avoyd it; and therefore that is the greater power.</p>
            <p>If a judgement be given in the Kings Bench, by the King himſelfe (as may be, and by the Law is intended) a writ of Errour, to reverſe this judgement, may be ſued before the King in Parliament, which writ muſt be granted by the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152499:8"/>Chancellor, upon bill indorſed by the King himſelfe, as the book is 1 <hi>H.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 7.19.6</note> 7.19.6. And the forme of the writ of Error is, that it being directed to the Chiefe Juſtice of the Kings Bench,
<note place="margin">Lib. ntrac. fol. 302. c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Quia in recordo &amp; proceſſu, ac etiam in redditione ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicii loquelae, quae fuit in Curiâ noſtrâ coram nobis, Error in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervenit manifeſtus ad grave damnum, &amp;c. Nos errorem (ſi quis fuerit) modo debito corrigi, &amp; partibus praedictis plenam &amp; celerem juſtitiam fieri volentes, in hâc parte vobis manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quòd Recordum &amp; proceſſum loquela illius cum omnibus ea tangentibus, in praeſens Parliamentum noſtrum ſub ſigillo tuo diſtinctè &amp; apertè mittas, &amp; hoc breve, ut inſpectis, &amp;c. nos de Conſilio &amp; adviſamento Dominorum ſpiritualiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, ac Communitatis in Parliamento noſtro praedicto exiſtentis, ulterius pro errore illo corrigendo fieri faciamus quod de jure &amp; ſecundum legem &amp; conſuetudinem Regni noſtri Angliae fuerit faciendum.</hi> So you ſee the Appeale is from the King out of the Parliament, to the King in Parliament; the writ is in his name; the rectifying and correcting the errours is by him,
<note place="margin">The book is not ſo, that the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons ſhould meddle.</note> but with the aſſent of the Lords, and Commons, than which there can be no ſtronger evidence to prove, that his power out of Parliament is ſubordinate to his power in Parliament; for in Acts of Parliament, be they lawes, grounds, or whatſoever elſe, the Act and power is the Kings, but with the aſſent of the Lords and Commons, which maketh it the moſt ſoveraigne and ſupreame power above all, and controulable by none. Beſides this right of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, there be others in the Kingdome of the ſame nature: As the power to make lawes; the power of Naturaliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the power of erection of arbitrary government; the power to judge without appeale; the power to legitimate: all which doe belong to the King only in Parliament. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there be of the ſame nature, that the King may exerciſe out of Parliament, which right is growne unto him in them, more in thoſe others by the uſe and practice of the Common-wealth: as denization, coynage, making warre: which power the King hath time out of minde practiſed, without the gain-ſaying and murmuring of his ſubjects: But theſe other powers before mentioned have ever beene
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152499:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>executed by him in Parliament, and not otherwiſe, but with the reluctation of the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Can any man give me a reaſon, why the King can only in Parliament make lawes? No man ever read any law, whereby it was ſo ordained; and yet no man ever read that any King practiſed the contrary: Therefore it is the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall right of the Kingdome, and the very naturall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our State and policy, being one of the higheſt rights of ſoveraigne power: So it is in naturalization, legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation, and the reſt of that ſort before recited.</p>
            <p>It hath been alleaged that thoſe which in this Cauſe have enforced their reaſons from this Maxime of ours <hi>(That the King cannot alter the Law)</hi> have diverted from the queſtion.</p>
            <p>I ſay under favor they have not; for that in effect is the very queſtion now in hand; for if he alone out of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may impoſe, he altereth the Law of England in one of theſe two maine fundamentall points. He muſt either take his Subjects goods from them, without aſſent of the party, which is againſt the Law; or elſe he muſt give his owne Letters Pattents, the force of a Law, to alter the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his ſubjects goods, which is alſo againſt the Law.</p>
            <p>That the King of England cannot take his ſubjects goods, without their conſent, it need not be proved more then a principall; it is <hi>jus indigena</hi> an old homeborne right, declared to be Law by divers ſtatutes of the Realme: As in 34. E. 3. cap. 2. That no office of the Kings,
<note place="margin">34. <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 2.</note> or of his heires, ſhall take any goods of any manner of perſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the aſſent and good will of the party, to whom the goods belonged. The ſame is declared in many other ſtatutes made againſt priſages and purveyances. Neither have ever any Kings attempted to go plainly &amp; directly againſt that right; but have deviſed certaine legall colours and ſhadowes for their wrongfull doing in that kind,
<note place="margin">Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Loans or Privie Scales, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence</note> which I doe find were of three ſorts: by way of Commiſſion; by way of Loan; by way of Benevolence. Commiſſions of another were the moſt inſolent; for they went out (as it were by authority to levy ayd of the people upon great neceſſity of the Common wealth) Theſe were condemned in Parliament 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152499:9"/>
               <hi>Num.</hi> 16. upon a grevious complaint made of the uſe of them by the Commons, unto the King in Parliament: wherein the people doe pray the King, that he would be pleaſed to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how at the parliament held the 17. year of his raign, and at the laſt Parliament,
<note place="margin">That is, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> it was then accorded, and granted by their ſaid Lord the King and his counſell, that there ſhould goe out no commiſſions out of chauncery for hobbeleries, Archers, and other charges to be levied upon the people, if they were not granted in Parliament; which ordinances were not obſerved; by reaſon whereof, the people were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhed and decayed, for which they prayed the King that he would be pleaſed to take pity of his people, and the ordinances and grants made to his people in Parliament to affirme and hold; And that if ſuch Commiſſions goe out without aſſent of Parliament, that the Commons, which are grieved thereby, may have writs of <hi>ſuperſedeas,</hi> according to the ſaid Ordinance, and that the people be not bound to obey them.</p>
            <p>To this the Kings anſwer is:</p>
            <q>Siul tiel impoſition fuit fait per grand neceſſitie, &amp; ceo del aſſent des Prelates, Countes, Barons, &amp; aut grandes &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes des Commons adon<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> preſents, Neant moins noſtre Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior le Roy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne voet que tiel impoſition non duement fait, ſoit treit in conſequence, eins voet que les ordinaunces dont ceſt petition fait mention ſoit bienment gardes.</q>
            <p>The lateſt time that ever King attempted that courſe of exaction was 17.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stowes</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. 17. <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>H.</hi> 8. upon the taking of the French King at <hi>Pavie,</hi> by the forces of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth: Cardinall <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> having a purpoſe to put the King into a warre, about that quarrell, and finding his cophers empty, adviſed this way, to ſend out Commiſſions, and by them to levie ayd of the people, according to the value of their eſtate; But this gave ſuch diſcontent to the whole Realme, that it cauſed in many places an actuall rebellion; and the Cardinall being called to give an account of this bad advice, did juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this fact by the example of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who adviſed <hi>Pharaoh</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152499:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>to take the fifth part of his ſubjects goods: But when hee ſaw that would not ſerve the turne, he falſely laid it upon the Judges, informing the King, he did it by their advice, being reſolved by them of the lawfulneſſe of the fact. So you ſee that great Churchmen found more ſafety in matter of government of our Common-wealth, in making a falſe report of a point of the Common-law, than in a true text of the Scripture. And if any Churchmen will endeavour by application of the text of Scripture, to overthrow the ancient lawes, and liberties of the Kingdome, I would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe them to be admoniſhed by the ill ſucceſſe of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, in this particular action, and by the miſerable cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe of his whole life and fortunes.
<note place="margin">Loans and Privie Seales.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Loanes, and appreſts were thoſe, which we call Privie Seales, which though they were more moderate in ſhew, yet being made againſt the good will of the parties, were as injurious indeed as the other. The Commons in Parliament,
<note place="margin">Rot. pat. 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi> 16.</note> 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Num.</hi> 16. made a grievous complaint to the King againſt the uſe of them, and prayed, that none from thenceforth ſhould be compelled to make loans againſt their will, and they gave this reaſon in their petition: for that it is againſt reaſon, and the franchiſe of the land, and prayed that reſtitution might bee made, to thoſe that have made ſuch loanes.</p>
            <p>To this the Kings reſcript was; <hi>It pleaſeth our Lord the King, it be ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, came in thoſe kinde of exactions,
<note place="margin">Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</note> which were termed by the faire name of <hi>Benevolences;</hi> but they became ſo odious, as they gave the occaſion of a good law to bee made againſt themſelves, and againſt all other ſhifts, and devices, by what new termes ſoever impoſed upon the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: the Law is 1. <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. and is thus:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> The King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring how the Commons of this his Realme, by n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and unlawfull inventions, and inordinate covetiſe, againſt the law of this Realme, have beene put to great ſervitude, and important charges and exactions, and eſpecially by a new impoſition called a Benevolence, enacteth by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice &amp;c. That the Subjects and Commons of this land from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152499:10"/>henceforth ſhall in no wiſe be charged by any ſuch charges, or impoſitions called a Benevolence, nor by ſuch like thing.</p>
            <p>But if you will deny, that the King doth in this caſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke the goods of his ſubject without his aſſent, then you muſt fall upon mine other alternative propoſition; That the Kings Patent hath in this caſe the power of a law, to alter property: for how can he recover the impoſed by a legall courſe of proceeding, and by judgement in his Court, but upon a title precedent him, before the action brought, which title muſt bee a property in the ſame impoſed? and how cometh he by that property, but by his owne Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, by which he declareth he will have that ſame as an impoſition? For the judgement giveth not the right, but only doth manifeſt and declare it, and giveth execution of it: So in this point, the queſtion is, whether the Kings Patent hath the force and power of the Law, or not: for if it bee not maintained that it hath, it can never be concluded, that he can transferre the property of his ſubjects goods to himſelfe, without the aſſent of them; for <hi>quod meum est, ſine facto meo alterius fieri non poteſt.</hi> And if you give this power to the Kings Patent, you ſubject the law, and take away all rules and bounds of ſetled govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and leave in the ſubject no property of his owne, neither doe you by this advance the Kings power and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative,
<note place="margin">Bracton <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> but you make him no King; for as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rex eſt ubi dominatur lex, non voluntas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So we ſee that the power of impoſing, and power of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Lawes are <hi>convertibilia &amp; coincidentia;</hi> and whoſoever can doe the one, can doe the other; And this was the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Sir <hi>Iohn Forteſcue</hi> that reverend and honourable Judge, a very learned profeſſor of the Common Law, and chiefe Juſtice of the Kings Bench,
<note place="margin">Forteſcu <hi>de laudibus Leg. Ang. cap.</hi> 9.</note> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s words are theſe in his book, <hi>De laudibus Legum Angliae cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Non Poteſt Rex Angliae ad libitum leges mutare regni ſui; principatu namque nedum regali, ſed &amp; politico ipſe dominatur: Si regali tantum praeeſſet iis, leges mutare poſſet; tallagia quoque, &amp; cateraonera imponere, ipſis inconſultis, quale dominium leges civiles indicant, cum dicunt quod principi pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerit,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152499:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>legis habet vigorem; ſed longè aliter poteſt Rexpoliticis imperans, quia nec leges ipſe ſine ſubditorum aſſenſu mutare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit, nee Subjectum populum renitentem enerare peregrinis impoſitionibus.</hi> In which place I muſt intepret unto you, that <hi>peregrinae impoſitiones</hi> be not ſtrange and unheard of impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as was urged by the worthy gentleman that ſpake laſt; but impoſitions upon traffique into, and out of forrain Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, which is the very thing in queſtion:
<note place="margin">Forteſcue de laud. Leg. Ang. <hi>cap.</hi> 36.</note> further in the thirty ſixth Chapter, he ſayeth, of the King of England, <hi>Neque Rex ibidem per ſe, aut miniſtros ſuos tallagia, Subſidiae, aut alia quaevis onera imponit ligeis ſuis, aut leges corum mutat, velnovas condit, ſine conceſſione vel aſſenſu totius regni ſui in Parliamento.</hi> So he maketh theſe two powers of making Law, and impoſing to be concomitant in the ſame hand, and that the one of them is not without the other; He gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the ſame reaſon for this, as we doe now, but in other words, becauſe (as he ſaith) in England it is <hi>principatus mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp; politicus,</hi> the King hath his Soveraigne power in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, aſſiſted and ſtrengthened with the conſent of the whole kingdome: and therefore theſe powers are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by him only in Parliament. In other Countreyes they admit the ground of the Civil Law, <hi>quod principi pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerit, legis habet vigorem;</hi> Becauſe they have an abſolute power to make Law, they have alſo a power to impoſe, which hath the force of a Law in transferring property.
<note place="margin">Ph. Com. <hi>l</hi> 4 <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>l</hi> 5. <hi>ca.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Philip Comynes,</hi> that lived at that time, in his fourth book the firſt chapter, the fifth booke, the eighth chapter, taketh notice of this policie of England, and commends it above all other States, as ſetled in moſt ſecurity: And further to our purpoſe layeth this ground, That a King cannot take one penny from his Subjects without their conſent, but it is violence. And you may there note the miſchiefs that grew to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of France, by the voluntary impoſitions firſt brought in by <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeventh, and ever ſince continued, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed to the utter impoveriſhment of the Common people, &amp; the loſſe of their free Councell of three eſtates: And if this power of impoſing were quietly ſetled in our Kings, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what is the greateſt uſe they make of aſſembling of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152499:11"/>which is the ſupply of money, I doe not ſee any likelihood to hope for often meetings in that kind; becauſe they would provide themſelves by that other meanes. And thus much for my firſt reaſon grounded upon the naturall conſtitution of the policie of our kingdome, and the publike right of our nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Com. Law.</note> For the point of Common Law, which is my ſecond Reaſon, it hath been well debated, and nothing left unſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that can be ſayd in it; and therefore I will decline to ſpeak of that, which other men have well diſcuſſed, and the rather, for that there is nothing in our Law-book directly, and in point of this matter; neither is the word <hi>(impoſition)</hi> found in them,
<note place="margin">Dier. 1. E. 165.</note> untill the caſe in my L. <hi>Dier,</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 165: for we ſhall finde this buſineſſe of an higher ſtrain, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes handled elſewhere, as afterwards ſhall appeare: yet I will offer ſome anſwers to ſuch objections, as have been made on the contrary in point of Common Law, and have not been much ſtood upon by others to be anſwered.</p>
            <p>The objections that have been made are theſe; that from the firſt Book of the Law, to the laſt, no man ever read any thing againſt the Kings power of impoſing; No judgement was ever given againſt it, in any of the Kings Courts at Weſtminſter: Other points of prerogative as high as this, diſputed and debated, his exceſſe in them limited, as in the book of 42.
<note place="margin">42. Aſs. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Aſs. pl.</hi> 5. where the Judges took away a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from one, that had power given by it to him under the great Seale, to take ones perſon, and to ſeiſe his goods before he was indicted.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. E. Dier. 175.</note> So Maſter <hi>Scrogs</hi> caſe, 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>El. Dier.</hi> 175. the power of the King in making a Commiſſion to determine a queſtion of right, depending between two parties notably debated, and ruled againſt the King, that hee could not grant it.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that cauſes of this nature (of which the queſtion now handled is) have ever been taken to be of that extraordinary conſequence, in point of the Common right of the whole kingdome, that the State would never truſt any of the Courts of ordinary juſtice with the deciding of them; but aſſumed the cogniſance of them into the high Court of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152499:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Parliament, as the fitteſt place to decide matters,
<note place="margin">2. Ed. 3.7.</note> ſo much concerning the whole body of the kingdome, As 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.7. it appeares, that <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. had granted a Charter to the men of great <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> that all the ſhips of Merchants, comming to the port of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> ſhould land their goods at their haven, and not at any other haven at that port, as at <hi>Garneſton,</hi> and little <hi>Yarmonth,</hi> which were members of that port This was very inconvenient for the Merchants, and a great hurt to traffique, and therefore the Charter was queſtioned in the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. and adjudged good by the Counſell: but the parties not contented with this judgement, in the ſecond yeer of King <hi>E.</hi> 3. by an order in Parliament made upon a petition there exhibeted againſt this grant, brought a <hi>Scire facias</hi> out of the Chancery returnable in the kings bench, to queſtion againe the lawfullneſſe of the Patent, and in that ſuit, the cauſe was notably Debated, and thoſe reaſons much inſiſted upon that have been enforced in this caſe; As that of the Kings power in the cuſtodie of the ports: But the matter ſo depending in the ordinary Court of juſtice, a Writ came out of the Parliament, and did adjourne it thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe, where it gave occaſion of a good Law to be made, to prevent the like grants, and to make them voyd notwithſtanding any judgement given upon them, and to make ſuch judgements alſo void. The Statute is, 9. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">9. E. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. everyal en and deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen may carry his Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe where it pleaſed him, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any Charter granted or judgment thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 16. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> And in the Parliament rolles, 2. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>num.</hi> 109. we finde a notable record, which gives warrant for the proceeding in Parliament, in this manner as hath been in this Caſe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the judgement in the Exchequer, and declares to the Kingdome, that notwithſtanding the great wonder made by ſome men, nothing hath been done in this buſineſſe by thoſe that ſerve in the Parliament, but in imitation of their worthy predeceſſors in the very like caſe. In the ſecond yeere of <hi>H.</hi> 4. the Commons ſhew that in the time of <hi>R.</hi> 2. by the meanes of <hi>John Waltham,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Saliſbury,</hi> Treaſurer of England, wrongfully without authority of Parliament, and by reaſon of a judgement given in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. <hi>R.</hi> 2. by the Barons there againſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Merchants of <hi>Briſtow,</hi> and other places, paſſage had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152499:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>been taken for wines, otherwiſe than in ancient times had been, and therefore they prayed, they might pay their priſe wines, in the manner they had uſed to pay, notwithſtanding any judgement given in the Exchequer, or other ordinance made by the ſaid Treaſurer, contrary to the ancient uſage; which petition the King granted, and the judgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon became voyde, and the priſage wine hath been paid contrary to the judgement ever ſince.</p>
            <p>In 1.
<note place="margin">1. El. Dier 165.</note> 
               <hi>El. Dier.</hi> 165. upon the complaint, made by the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, of the impoſitions ſet upon cloth by Queene <hi>Mary</hi> by her abſolute power, without aſſent of Parliament; the cauſe was thought too weighty to bee decided in any one Court; but (as it appeareth in the book) it was referred to all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> who divers times had conference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. So it may well be, there is nothing againſt it in our yeere books, for there is nothing of it.</p>
            <p>Another objection was this, which was made in the laſt argument, <hi>viz.</hi> That Cuſtome is originally due by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of <hi>England,</hi> It can then have no other ground or cauſe; but meerly by the Kings royall prerogative, as a right and duty originally belonging to his Crowne: which if it be, it muſt neceſſarily follow he may impoſe, for that is but the exerciſing of that right. To prove this was alledged the caſe 39.
<note place="margin">39 E. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3.13. by which caſe it appeareth, that King <hi>Iohn</hi> had a cuſtome of eight pence on a tonn of wine in the part of South-hampton, but the book doth not tell you that the King had it by prerogative, and he might have it aſwell otherwiſe: as by preſcription, or convention, which ſhall rather be intended, by reaſon of the certainty of the ſumme paied; for if it were by prerogative, he might take ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more, ſometimes leſſe at his will, the right being inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and the quantity limitted onely by his owne Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<note place="margin">18. El Dier 352.</note> A common perſon may have ſuch a cuſtome certaine, as, 18. <hi>El. Dier</hi> 352. the Maior of <hi>London</hi> hath the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth part of ſalt brought into the City by Aliens, which is a great impoſition, but is good by preſcription originally and hath received greater ſtrength ſince, by acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made, for the confirmation of the liberties and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152499:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>cuſtomes of the City of <hi>London.</hi> So it appeareth,
<note place="margin">Dier 43.</note> that <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Britaine</hi> had Cuſtome of the ſhips that arrived at his port of little <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> worth twenty pounds <hi>per an.</hi> And theſe inſtances doe inferre, that a Cuſtome may bee otherwiſe then by prerogative, and therefore it is no good argument to conclude, the King had ſuch a cuſtome, Therefore he had it by prerogative.</p>
            <p>The booke in 30. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Dier</hi> 43.
<note place="margin">30. Hen. 8. Dier 43.</note> was much preſſed on this point, which ſayeth that cuſtome belonged to the King at Common Law, and doth inſtance in wooll, woll fells, and leather begun at the Common Law, but abridged by the Satute of 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 21. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">14. Ed. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 21. <hi>ſtatn.</hi>
               </note> r. but this appeareth to be a great errour, and miſtaking in the booke; for we doe finde that that cuſtome of woolls, wooll-fells, and Leather was begun by a grant in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as appeareth in ſtatute 15. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 7. the words be Granted to us by the Commonalty aforeſaid, and the laſt mention before was that the King had granted to the Biſhops, Earles, Barons, and all the Commonalty of land, &amp;c. <hi>Novem.</hi> 3. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. the King recited in his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patents, That <hi>Prelati magnates actota Communitas mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum Regni,</hi> granted this new cuſtome. And ſo the ground and motive of that opinion being falſe, all groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon that muſt needs be erroneous.</p>
            <p>It was objected that the King holdeth at this day the encreaſe of foure pence in the pound, over due cuſtome, payd by Merchants Aliens according to the purport of the <hi>Charta mercatoria</hi> 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Rot. char. 31. E. 1. <hi>nu.</hi> 44. in Turri</note> by meere right of prerogative at the Common Law; for by that grant of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants he cannot hold it, they being no body politick at the time of the grant; and therefore the grant is meerely voyd to binde in ſucceſsion, And yet the Merchants Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens doe pay it at this day.</p>
            <p>It is agreed, that by the Common-law a contract with a number not incorporate, bindeth not ſucceſſion; but we muſt take notice, that they, by whom that grant was made, of the augmentation of Cuſtome, by three-pence in the pound, and other encreaſes, 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1. were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152499:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Merchants aliens, who by the law of Merchants, and Nations may contract to binde their ſucceſſours in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of traffique: for their contracts are not ruled by the Common law of the Land, but by the law of Nations, <hi>&amp; per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egem Mercatoriam,</hi> as the book caſe is, 13. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.10. and there was a good conſideration given them by the King for this encreaſe of cuſtome: as diſcharge of priſe Wines for two ſhillings the Tonn, and other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, which all Merchants aliens hold and enjoy at this day, by force of that contract made 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1. For a ſtranger payeth now but two ſhillings the Tonn for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, whereas it ſtandeth an Engliſh man in much more: ſo as the rule of commutative juſtice maketh the contract availeable to the King againſt the Merchants, becauſe he parteth with part of his priſage to the Merchant, and maketh it availeable to the Merchant againſt the King, becauſe he giveth him encreaſe of cuſtome above that is due by law.
<note place="margin">27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c</hi> 26</note> But the ſtatute of 27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore cited doth make this point cleare without ſcruple, which confirmeth the Charter of 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1. entirely, and by that the encreaſe of cuſtome by three-pence in the pound, which is by name mentioned in the ſtatute, is now due by act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>If you will have the King hold this encreaſe of cuſtome by Prerogative, you goe directly againſt his meaning; for it appeareth by that which preſently followed this grant, that the King took this encreaſe of cuſtome by way of contract only, and not by Prerogative; for the ſame yeare following he directeth his writs to the officers of his ports, reciting the contract made with the Aliens by <hi>Charta Mercatoria,</hi> adding further, that ſome Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens were willing to pay the like cuſtome, upon the ſame immunities to them to be granted, and doth aſſigne his officers to gather it, but with this clauſe, <hi>Si gratanter &amp; abſque coertione ſolvere voluerint, ita quod aliquem Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorem de regno, &amp; poteſtate noſtrâ ad praeſtationes &amp; cuſtumas hujuſmodi invito ſolvendas nullatenùs diſtringatis.</hi> Nothing can more plainly expreſſe, that the Kings inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152499:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>was not to demand this by way of Prerogative, but by force of the contract. If there were ſuch a Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in the Crowne as of right to have cuſtome; how commeth it to paſſe, this Prerogative never yet had fruit or effect? for this I can maintaine, that the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath not one penny cuſtome, or impoſition upon merchandizes elder than the fourth yeare of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> that hee holdeth not by act of Parliament, and by the peoples grant: The eldeſt that he hath is that of wools, woolfells, and lether, and that is by act of Parliament, as appeareth in the Statute 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.
<note place="margin">25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> the tonnage and poundage by Parliament in the firſt yeare of every Kings reigne.</p>
            <p>The Aliens encreaſe of cuſtome by Parliament 27. <hi>E.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 26. then this Prerogative hath been much neglected, that it was never called on to be put in execution, untill now of late yeares.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſtatutes made for reſtraining our Kings, from the exerciſe of this pretended Prerogative,
<note place="margin">Statutes 3.</note> which is the third matter I ſtand upon: Thoſe that have maintained the Kings Prerogative in this point, have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to interpret thoſe ſtatutes, to extend only to reſtraine him from impoſing upon wool, woolfells, and lether, which are ſtaple commodities: And the reaſon they give for this reſtraint, more than for other goods, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King, by ſtatute, is reſtrained to a cuſtome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine for thoſe commodities, as the halfe mark a ſack of wooll, and halfe a mark three hundred woollfels, and thirteene ſhillings foure pence a laſt of lether; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore great reaſon he ſhould not exceed this cuſtome in theſe commodities.</p>
            <p>This objection receiveth many anſwers: Firſt it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth both by the expreſſe letter of divers of the Lawes made in this point by the occaſion that induced the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Lawes, and by the execution of them, that all other wares and merchandiſes, aſwell as thoſe of the ſtaple, were within the purpoſe and intent of thoſe Lawes: Secondly, the reaſon aleadged, why there ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152499:14"/>for the ſtaple commodities, rather than for the other, is miſtaken; for the Lords and Commons did grant to <hi>E.</hi> 1. by act of Parliament the cuſtome of the halfe mark for wooll, woolfels, and lether, which was matter of mere grace and liberality, and includeth no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint in it, but rather a favourable extention, quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſenſe of the objection; according to that rule of interpretation, <hi>Gratioſa ampliari decet, odioſa reſtringi.</hi> And admit ſome Lawes be made expreſly to reſtraine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions upon wooll, woollfels, and lether, by reaſon that the occaſion of making ſuch Lawes was the actuall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, upon thoſe goods at that time, ſhall we not by good conſtruction, <hi>Secundum mentem extenſivum legis,</hi> extend this law to other wares and merchandizes, that are within the ſame miſchiefe? If we look to the reaſon of the law, we ſhall make no doubt of it; for that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the impoſitions were without aſſent of Parliament, not becauſe they were upon ſuch, and ſuch commodities. Beſides thoſe Lawes ſo made are <hi>declarativae juris anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui, non introductivae novi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the enumeration of thoſe ſtatutes, which I conceive make directly to this purpoſe, I will endeavour rather to anſwer the objections made againſt them, than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the ſenſe and meaning of them, which is very plaine and open, and needs no interpretation. The firſt ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute enforced is, <hi>Mag. charta cap.</hi> 30. made in the ninth yeare of <hi>H.</hi> 3. by which it is enacted, that all Merchants ſhall have free egreſſe, and regreſſe, out of, and into this Realme, with their goods and merchandizes, to buy, and ſell, <hi>ſine omnibus malis tolnetis per antiquas, &amp; rectas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudines:</hi> in which words we may inferre, that both the uſe and right of impoſing are abſolutely excluded, and debarred; for <hi>Conſuetudo,</hi> which in this caſe is to be taken for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage,</hi> which is <hi>mos</hi> (not improperly for <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium,</hi> a duty paid in money, as our Engliſh word Cuſtome, in one ſenſe doth ſignifie) implyeth a begining, and continuance by conſent, and will of the parties, not by power, and enforcement which cannot be a cuſtome;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152499:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and therefore it cannot be an impoſition: for that ariſeth mercly out of the will and power of their impoſer, and is againſt the will of him, upon whoſe goods it is ſet: But take <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> either for <hi>mos</hi> or <hi>portorium,</hi> the epithetes with which it is qualified <hi>antiquum,</hi> and <hi>rectum,</hi> doe deſcribe it to bee of that nature, that it cannot be an impoſition: for <hi>antiquum,</hi> in legall conſtruction, is that which is time out of minde, that is not an impoſition: for then, by continuance of time, it ſhould grow aright by preſcription, and were juſtifiable: <hi>Rectum</hi> implyeth a limitted right, which inferreth, there may be a wrong and exceeding of that right, which is not in impoſitions: for if there be a right in the King to impoſe, the quantity, time, and other circumſtances are in his diſcretion; the right is illimited: And if he ſet on never ſo great an impoſition, there is as much right in it, as if it be never ſo ſmall: the exceſſe maketh it a burthen, but not a wrong.</p>
            <p>We may further obſerve, that in the ſtatute, <hi>malum tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netum,</hi> which is evill toll, is ſet downe by way of antithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis to <hi>antiqua</hi> and <hi>recta conſuetudo;</hi> by which is inferred, that exactions upon wares and merchandizes, not quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with theſe two properties of <hi>antiquum</hi> and <hi>rectum,</hi> are evill and unjuſt. This is made more evident by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in the Tower of the ſixteenth yeare of <hi>H.</hi> 3. which was a mandat ſent by the King to the Cuſtomers of his ports for the execution of this law made in 9. <hi>H.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">Rot. clauſ. 16. <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi> 20</note> whereby it is commanded, <hi>Quod omnibus Mercatoribus in portum ſuum venientibus cum vinis, &amp; aliis merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zis ſcire faciant, quod ſalvò &amp; ſecurè in terram Angliae veniant cum vinis &amp; mercandizis ſuis, faciendo inde rectas &amp; debitas conſuetudines, nec ſibi timeant de malis tolnetis, quae us faciat Rex, vel in terrâ ſuâ fieri permittat.</hi> By this record the word <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> is interpreted to be <hi>mos,</hi> not <hi>portorium,</hi> otherwiſe it ſhould have beene <hi>ſolvendo conſuetudines,</hi> not <hi>faciendo.</hi> Alſo theſe words <hi>antiquum &amp; rectum</hi> in the ſtatute in this writ are <hi>rectum &amp; debitum,</hi> which doth more enforce a certainty of right and duty,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152499:15"/>which by no meanes can be intended in impoſitions.</p>
            <p>Objections againſt this law were made in the laſt argument. Firſt, that it was made for Aliens: this is true; the words of the Law doe plainly ſhew it was made for Aliens: but if the State was ſo carefull to provide for them; ſhall we not judge that with Denizens it was ſo already? and that this ſtatute was made to extend that liberty by act of Parliament to Aliens, which Denizens had by the Common law: ſucceeding times did ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of it,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> as appeareth by the ſtatute of 2. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 9, the words are, that all Merchants, ſtrangers, and Princes may goe and come with their merchandizes in <hi>England,</hi> after the tenor of the great Charter, and that writs bee thereupon ſent to all the Sheriffs in <hi>England,</hi> and to Maiors, and Bayliffs of good townes where need ſhall require.</p>
            <p>A ſecond objection was made in the laſt argument, out of theſe words of the ſtatute of <hi>M. Chart.</hi> that Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants might freely traffique, <hi>Niſi publicè antea prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biti fuerint:</hi> by which was enforced, that the King had power to reſtraine and prohibit traffique; therefore to impoſe. It is agreed, there may be a publick reſtraint of traffique, upon reſpects of the common good of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but whether that which is called <hi>publica prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio</hi> in the ſtatute, be intended by the King alone, or by act of Parliament, is a queſtion: for ſuch reſtraints have ſtill beene by Parliament. But admit the King may make a reſtraint of traffique in part, for ſome publick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the common wealth, he doth this in point of protection, as truſted by the Common wealth, to doe that which is for the publick good of the kingdome; but if he uſe this truſt to make a gaine and benefit by impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that is a breach of the truſt, and a ſale of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and protection. But more of this ſhall be hereafter ſpoken in the anſwering of the maine objections.</p>
            <p>The next law is that notable ſtatute of <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> 1. in the 28 yeare of his reigne made upon the very point in queſtion: the words are theſe; And foraſmuch as the more part
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152499:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Commonaltie of this Realme finde themſelves ſore grieved with the male toll of Woolls, that is, to wit, a toll of forty ſhillings, for every ſack of Wooll, and have petitioned to us for to releaſe the ſame; Wee at their requeſt have clearly releaſed it, and have gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for us and our heires, that wee ſhall not take ſuch things, without their common conſent and good will, ſaving to us and our heires the cuſtomes of Woolls, Skins, and Leather granted before by the Commonalty aforeſaid. Againſt the application of this Law to the queſtion now in hand, many objections were made, ſome out of matter precedent to the Law, ſome out of the Law it ſelfe, ſome out of matter ſubſequent and following after the Law: For matter precedent;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham</hi> in <hi>E.</hi> 1. fo. 71.72.73. edit. per <hi>W. Cam den</hi> impreſ. <hi>Francofur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</hi> 1603.</note> It was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected out of <hi>Tho. Walſingham</hi> an Hiſtoriograper of good credit, that Writ of that time when the Satute was made, That in the petition of grievances given to King <hi>E.</hi> 1. by the people in the 25. yeere of his raigne, upon which petition the ſtatute was made, that they found themſelves not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in point of right, but in point of exceſſe; the words are, <hi>Communitas ſentit ſe gravatam, de vectigali lanarum quod nimis est oneroſum,</hi> viz. <hi>de quolibet ſacco</hi> 40. <hi>s. &amp; de lanâ fractâ ſeptem marcas;</hi> So they expreſſe the cauſe of their griefe, that it was too heavie; which is to bee applyed to the point of exceſſe, not of right.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that if the words had been <hi>(quia ost nimis oneroſum)</hi> this conſtruction might have been made out of them; becauſe the word <hi>(quia)</hi> had induced a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the cauſe of that which was formerly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: but the words are <hi>(quod nimis oneroſum)</hi> which doth onely poſitively affirme that the impoſition, <hi>de facto,</hi> was intolerable for the greatneſſe of it, which doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore admit that it is tolerable, in reſpect of the right the King had to impoſe. But this is made cleare by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall word precedent in the preamble of the petition, which doth evidently inferre, they grounded their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint upon point of right, not upon point of of exceſſe; the words are theſe, <hi>Tota terra communitas ſentit ſe valdè gravatam, quia non tractantur ſecundum leges, &amp; conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152499:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>terrae, ſecundum quas tractari anteceſſores ſui ſolebant habere, ſed voluntariè excluduntur.</hi> After which preamble, among the particulars, this of forty ſhillings upon a ſack of Wooll is ranked, but with a dependencie of that expreſſed in the preamble, for the point of right. But ſeeing wee light upon Hiſtory, which though it bee of ſmall authority in a Law argument; yet being the Hiſtory of our owne Realme, hath fit and proper uſe in the common counſell of the Realme,
<note place="margin">Matth. Weſtm. fo. 430. Edit. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r H. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile mil. Francofur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti 1601.</note> I will purſue it a little further. Out of <hi>Matth. Weſtm.</hi> a Writer, that lived much nearer the time of the Law made, then <hi>Thomas Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> he ſaith, That the Commons by their petitions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, <hi>Ne Rex de coetero tallagia uſurparet, &amp; voluntarias ſuper his inductas exactiones de coetero quaſi in irritum revocaret;</hi> by which it appeareth, that the point of the complaint was, that the exactions layd on them were vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, that is, at the Kings will, without aſſent of Parliament. Out of the Law it ſelfe, it hath much been preſſed, as firſt the Commons made petition to the King, wherupon they inferre out of the nature of the word (peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that their proceeding was by way of grievance, for the exceſſe and inconvenience, as a matter of grace, not in courſe of juſtice for the wrong.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that conſidering the qualitie of the parties to this action, it being betweene the King and the ſubject; duty and good manners doth induce gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe and humilitie of termes, without blemiſh, or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of the force of right. It is according to the demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 5.15.</note> cap. 9. v. 15. <hi>Though I were juſt, yet would I not anſwer, but I would make ſupplication to my judge.</hi> But in our formes of Law, be the right of the ſubject never ſo cleare, manifeſt, and acknowledged by all; yet if his own be detained from him by the King, he hath no other writ or action to recover, but a meere petition, <hi>Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat celſitudini, &amp;c.</hi> So as if the word petition to the King inferre defect of right in the petitioner; there can be no caſe where the King can doe the ſubject wrong.</p>
            <p>A ſecond objection out of the body of the Law is, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152499:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>the King doth releaſe that impoſition of forty ſhillings, which implyeth a right ſetled in him. But to this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that it is no neceſſarie inference, that whereſoever a releaſe of right is: for it is uſed for claime only, or where poſſeſſion was, though wrongfull, and that <hi>in majorem ſecuritatem, quia abundans cautela non nocet;</hi> But in this caſe, a releaſe was very expedient, and for ſome reſpect neceſſary, to extinguiſh a right the King had in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt the Marchants themſelves: For this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, though it were not ſet on by aſſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet was it not ſet on by the Kings abſolute power; but was granted to him by the Merchants themſelves who were to bee charged with it: ſo the grievance was the violation of the right of the people, in ſetting it on without their aſſent in Parliament, not the dammage that grew by it; for that did only touch the Merchants, who could not juſtly complaine thereof, becauſe it was their own act and grant.
<note place="margin">22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen. in Scac. Rem. Theſ.</note> This appeareth by two nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble records, the one 22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. A writ to the Treaſurer and Barons of the Exchequer in Ireland, to diſcharge the Merchants there, of impoſitions on Woolls; in which the King reciteth, <hi>Licet in ſubſidium Guerra Regis pro recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perandâ terrâ Vaſconiâ, mercatores gratanter conceſſerunt per biennium vel triennium, ſi tantum duraverit Guerra, de ſacco lanae, &amp;c.</hi> The other record is the Writ of publication that in 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. went out after the Statute of 25.
<note place="margin">In 26. F. 1. mem. Sca. Rem. Theſ.</note> in which Writ the King reciteth thus, <hi>Cum nos ad inſtantiam Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitatis Regni nostri remiſerimus cuſtumam</hi> 40. <hi>s. nobis nuper in ſubſidium Guerrae noctrae contra Regem Franciae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum, &amp;c.</hi> A third objection made out of the body of the Statute, by thoſe which have argued on the contrary part was upon theſe words, that the King would take (no ſuch things) without common conſent: by which words they conceived the intention of the Law, was limitted preciſely to impoſitions ſet upon wooll, and not on other commodities, which are not ſuch things, but other: And for this they alledge this reaſon, That it was not probable when the complaint was only for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152499:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>an impoſition on Wooll, that the King would give a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for other things not ſpoken of, for which there was no cauſe of complaint.</p>
            <p>To this a full anſwer is given many wayes: firſt out of the <hi>(Saving)</hi> in the Act, which extends to other things than to Wooll, as to Wooll-fells and Leather; therefore the purview of the act by theſe words (ſuch things) extendeth to more than the Wooll; for there needs no <hi>Saving,</hi> but for that which is contained in the purview. Secondly, the reaſon alledged, that no more by likelihood ſhould bee remedied, but for Wooll; becauſe only that was complained of, is falſe: For the complaint of the Commons was not only for this impoſition on Wooll; but divers other burthens and grievances of the like nature. And this will appeare if wee compare all the parts of the Law. the one with the other: for this Law is in the forme of a Charter written in French, and beginneth, <hi>Edward by the grace of God, &amp;c.</hi> And is an entire grant, and inſtrument without fractions, ſections, and Chapters, as it is now printed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it, next before this laſt clauſe concerning the impoſitions on Woolls, which in the printed Book is <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. That the King, for no buſineſſe from thenceforth, will take no manner of aydes, miſes, nor priſes, but by common aſſent. This word <hi>(miſes)</hi> in French ſignifieth properly impoſitions, derived of the word <hi>mitto,</hi> in Latine (to put) ſo the word (ſuch things) is a concluſion to all the premiſes, and hath relation not only to that which is made <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. by the Printer, and concerneth the male toll of Woolls; but to that precedent which is (all otheraydes) impoſitions, and takings.</p>
            <p>The Writ of publication of this Statute ſant out to all parts in 26.
<note place="margin">Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ac in 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Rem. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 1. maketh plaine this conſtruction, the words of it are, <hi>Concedentes quod cuſtumam illam velaliam, ſine voluntate, vel communi aſſenſu non capiamus:</hi> Theſe words <hi>(vel aliam)</hi> are indefinite, and extend to any other whatſoever, beſides that of Woolls. The Writ doth further diſcharge Merchants for the Commodities of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152499:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Wooll-fells, and Leather, which are not complained of by name in the Statute; and therefore the Law was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to other impoſitions, aſwell as to thoſe upon Woolls.</p>
            <p>The objection made out of matter ſubſequent to the Statute was this, that notwithſtanding this Law of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. impoſitions that before the ſtatute had bin ſet on other Merchandize than Woolls, were ſtill anſwered after the Statute; and for inſtance of this was alledged, that whereas 16. <hi>E.</hi> 1. an impoſition of 4. <hi>s.</hi>
               <note place="margin">16. <hi>E</hi> 1. <hi>Orig. R. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> the Tonn was ſet upon Wines brought into the Kingdome, an accompt was made of this in th' exchequer in 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. as by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords there appeareth; by which it ſeemeth that the Law of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. was not taken to extend to wines, and ſuch other Commodities, other than Woolls named in the Statute. It is true, ſuch an impoſition was ſet on by <hi>E.</hi> 1. in the ſixteenth yeere of his raign, and an accompt made for it 25. and 26.
<note place="margin">25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>de compt. T. Mich. R. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> But it appeareth by the record of the accompt, that it was made for the time ended before the Statute made: As from the eighteenth of <hi>May,</hi> 16 <hi>E.</hi> 1. to 23 <hi>Jul.</hi> 22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. But there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that ever any accompt was made for any money received for that impoſition, for the time after the Statute made; neither was it very willingly anſwered before; for it appeareth by the record, that it was ten yeere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſetting of it.</p>
            <p>The third Satute alledged on the behalfe of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is that 34. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. the words are theſe,
<note place="margin">34. <hi>E.</hi> 1. ca. 1.</note> No tallage or aide ſhall be taken or levied by us, or our heires in our Realme, without the good will and aſſent of our Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Earles, Barons, Knights, burgeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and other freemen of the land. Againſt this was objected, that this Statute was intended only upon the taxes &amp; impoſitions of things; The word <hi>Auxilium</hi> makes it cleare, that it is to be intended further then of things within the realme; for <hi>tallagium</hi> is commonly intended of Domeſticall taxes, but <hi>auxilium</hi> is the moſt uſuall terme for impoſitions upon goods imported and expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152499:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>as by the acts of Parliament by which ſuch impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are given to the King, in which they are called moſt commonly by the name of Aydes, as proceeding of good will and benevolence.</p>
            <p>The fourth Satute alledged on this part is that of 5.
<note place="margin">5. <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 14 Rot. Ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 14. juſt in point of the matter in queſtion; and therefore I will ſet it downe as I finde it <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> in the record in the tower, <hi>Enſement novelles cuſtomes ſont levies, &amp; ancients enhaunces come ſur levies drapes, vine, aver du pcis, &amp; aut choſes purguoy les Merchants veynont pluis vilement, &amp; meynes de bien, menynont en la terre, &amp; les Merchants eſtrangers de murront pluis longment que ils ſoloyent faier, pur le quel demoure les choſes ſont le pluis enhaunces que ils ne Soloyent eſtre, al dammage de roy, &amp; de ſon people. Nou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ordonomus que touts manners de male tolls levies puies de Coronement de Roy Ed. faier de Roy Henry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>irement ouſtes, &amp; de tout eſtreints pur touts jours, nient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iriſteant le Chartre que le dict Roy Ed. fiſt as Merchants aliens, pur ceo que il fuit fait contra le grand Char. &amp; encountre le Franchiſe de la City de Londres, &amp; ſans aſſent de Baronage, &amp;c. Savant neque dont al Roy le cuſtome de leynes, peulx, &amp; de quirs, &amp;c, ſi aver les doet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Law is recited, that by the leving of new couſtomes, and by the raiſing of old, traffique was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and all things made deare; And therefore all new impoſitions and cuſtomes were dſcharged <hi>Chartâ mercatoriâ,</hi> by which cuſtome was encreaſed on aliens, was taken away, and the reaſon alledged; Becauſe it was <hi>ſans aſſent de Baronage,</hi> and againſt the great Charter. And this is further which this clauſe, Saving to the King his cuſtome of wooll, woll-fells and Lether, <hi>Si aver les doet.</hi> Great warres have been raiſed againſt the credit of this Law in the Parliament houſe, and three things have been eſpecially objected againſt it; Firſt, that it is no Law, for it was enforced upon the King, by ſome of the nobility that were too ſtrong for him, the Realme being then in tumult and mutiny about the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152499:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>quarrell of <hi>Peirce</hi> of <hi>Gaveſton,</hi> ſo never had the Kings free conſent; but he gave way unto it for feare of greater miſchiefe: Secondly, that in it ſelfe it is unjuſt, as in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the cuſtome granted to the King by <hi>Charta mercatoria</hi> 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1. and in making doubt whether the King ſhould have the cuſtome of wools, &amp;c. by thoſe words, <hi>Saving it to him, Si aner les doet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third objection is, that if it were a Law, it is repealed.</p>
            <p>To theſe I give particular anſwers.</p>
            <p>To the firſt: that this ſtatute was made both at the inſtance of the King, and people, with a purpoſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention on all parts to ſettle things in a ſtay and order, both in the Kings houſe, and Common-wealth: the King and his nobles ſtanding in good termes, when this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was taken in hand; and it was begun and ended with great ſolemnity and ceremony: for the King in the third yeare of his reigne gave Commiſſion under his great Seale to 32. Lords ſpirituall and temporall;
<note place="margin">Com. 16. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 3. <hi>E.</hi> 2. Rot. or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din. 5. <hi>E.</hi> 2.</note> of which there were eleven Biſhops, eight Earles, and thirteene Barons; they being as Committees of the higher Houſe to deviſe ordinances, for the good government of of his houſe and his Realme. In which Commiſsion he doth for the honour of God, the good of him, and of his Realme, of his freewill graunt to the Prelates, Earles, and Barons, and others elected by the whole Kingdome, full power to ordaine the State of his houſe and Realme by ſuch ordinances, as by them ſhould bee made, to the honour of God, the honour and profit of holy Church, the honour of himſelfe, the profit of him and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, according to right and reaſon, and the oath hee made at his Coronation.</p>
            <p>Theſe joyning with others of diſcreet Commons in Parliament, and taking every of them a ſolemn oath for their ſincere demeanor in the buſineſſe, did make this and other ordinances, which were ſo well liked of by the King, that after they were made, hee took an oath to obſerve
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152499:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>them,
<note place="margin">Pullic. 3. Kal. Oct. 5. <hi>E.</hi> 2. Rot ordin. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 5. Oct. 5. <hi>E.</hi> 2. Rot. ordin.</note> and cauſed them to be publiſhed in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard by the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> by denouncing excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, againſt all that ſhould wilfully infringe them: And by his Letters Patents dated 5. <hi>Oct.</hi> 5. <hi>regni ſui,</hi> did ſend them through the Realme to be publiſhed, and from thenceforth to be obſerved, thereby ſignifying his great liking and approbation of them; after which they had the force and power of Lawes given unto them in the Parliament, in the fifth yeere of his raign.</p>
            <p>The ſecond obiection, which is the injuſtneſſe of the law, inſtanced in two points; the taking away of <hi>Charta mercatoria,</hi> and the doubting of the Kings right to the cuſtome of wolls, woll-fells and Lether, &amp;c. To the firſt of theſe, I deny it to be unjuſt, but to be according to the law of <hi>England,</hi> and liberty of the Kingdome: for that Charter did containe in it divers grants of things, which were not in the power of the King to grant, without aſſent of Parliament; as the triall <hi>per medietatem linguae,</hi> and other things tending to the alteration of the Law, and burdening of the people; and therefore that Charter never had his undoubted and ſetled force, until it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by act of Parliament, but lay aſleep almoſt twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeers together, without being put in execution, between 5. <hi>E.</hi> 2. and 27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. when it was confirmed, for the doubt that is ſuppoſed to be made in the ſtatute of the Kings right to the cuſtome of wooll, wooll-fells, and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I take it there is no ſuch doubt made: For the words (Saving the kings right to the cuſtome of woolls <hi>ſi aver les doet)</hi> have this conſtruction, that is, at ſuch times as hee ought to have it: ſo the word <hi>(ſi)</hi> hath the ſignification of <hi>(quando)</hi> for it had been a folly to have made a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of that, of the right whereof they had doubted, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it likely but that they would have taken it away, if it had not been lawfull; but there was no colour to doubt of the right of it, for it was given by act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ever continued in force without challenge, or exception to the lawfullneſſe of it.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152499:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The third objection is, That this Statute is repealed: To this I plead, <hi>Nullum vale recordum.</hi> If it be repealed it muſt be by Act of Parliament, for <hi>unumquod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſſoluitur i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem modis quibus eſt colligatum:</hi> I and others have ſearched the Records of the Realme, and endeavoured by all means to informe our ſelves of the truth herein, and we can finde no Act of Parliament of repeale: The truth is, ſome Kings finding theſe Lawes not to ſort to their wills and humours, have endevoured to ſuppreſſe them, but they didnever yet obtaine a repeale of them by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>But it is further urged, That although there were no formall repeale of the Law, yet it was never put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as a Law, but even preſently upon the making was rejected, and uſe and practiſe went quite againſt it: And for inſtance hereof, a Record was vouched that <hi>E.</hi> 2. held himſelfe ſo little bound by it, as that in the 11 yeare of his raigne he ſet an impoſition without aſſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon Wooll, Wooll-fels, Leather, Wines, Cloth, <hi>aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de pois,</hi> and divers other kinde of Merchandizes. To this I anſwer, that if it were true, that a diſtinct and impotent King, as he was, did contrary to the Law; doth this make the Law void and no Law: But if wee looke into the whole Record, and skanne this action of <hi>E.</hi> 2. from the beginning of it, unto the end, we ſhall finde it a very good inſtance to prove the practiſe and execution both of this Law of 5. <hi>E.</hi> 2. and of that in 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. for it is true that <hi>E.</hi> 2. in the 11 yeare of his raigne did borrow of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants a certaine ſumme of money above the due cuſtome of Wooll, Wooll-fels, Wine, <hi>averdepois,</hi> Leather, and ſuch other goods imported and exported; But it appeareth by the Record, hee tooke it but for one yeare; hee tooke it by the adviſe and counſell of the Merchants: and he took it <hi>per viam mutui.</hi> as a loane. The direction of the Writ is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. claus.</hi> 11. <hi>E</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Collectoribus mutui nobis per mercatores alienigenas &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digenas de certis rebus &amp; Merchandiſis uſque ad certum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus faciendi.</hi> This was done in good tearmes, he did not claime it as his right, but did borrow it, which I doe thinke is a good evidence againſt his right: But what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152499:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>of this? the State would not abide it, for all theſe faire ſhewes. And therefore afterwards the King ſendeth out other Writs by which he diſchargeth all merchandizes of this loan, ſaving onely Wooll, Wooll-fels, and Leather, and for the loane taken upon thoſe commodities, it was limitted to continue but untill Michaelmas after, and good ſecurity was given to the Merchants by the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to pay themſelves by way of defalcation out of the Cuſtomes which ſhould be due after Michaelmas, thoſe ſummes which were ſo borrowed of them. The words of the Record are worth the obſerving,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. finium</hi> 11. <hi>E.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Cum pro expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione guerrae Scotiae, &amp; alijs arduis &amp; urgentibus neceſſitatibus nobis multipliciter incumbentibus, pro quarum exoneratione quaſi infinitam pecuniam refundere oportebit, pecunia plurimum indigeamus in preſenti, &amp; nuper pro eo quod exitus regni &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum noſtrarum ſimul cumpecunia nobis in ſubventione prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſorum tam per Clerum quam Communitatem regni noſtri conceſſa ad ſumptus praedictos cum feſtinatione qua expediret faciendos, non ſufficiunt, exquirentes vias, &amp; modos quibus poſſemus pecuniam habere commodius &amp; decentius pro praemiſſis de conſilio &amp; adviſamento quorundam mercatorum tam alieni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genarum quam indigenarum viam invenimus infra ſcript, viz.</hi> And ſo ſetteth down the manner of the loan, and the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the payment of it: This (I take it) was neither an impoſition, nor a wrong in any reſpect. Alſo by the firſt Record it appeareth, that the loane ſet on Wines, <hi>averdepois,</hi> and ſuch other commodities, beſides Wooll, Wooll-fels and Leather were preſently diſcharged by <hi>E.</hi> 2. which ſheweth they were taken to be within the intent of the Statute of 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The fift Statute alledged on the behalfe of the ſubject is that 14.
<note place="margin">14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Stat.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Stat.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 21. by which the Commons pray the King to take no more then th'old cuſtome of the halfe marke. The King prayeth aide of the Commons for a time above the cuſtome upon his neceſſity of warres. And the concluſion is that by that Act the King doth grant that after the feaſt of Pentecoſt twelve moneths follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he will take no more of Wools, Wooll-fels &amp; Leather,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152499:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>but the old Cuſtome, and doth promiſe to charge, ſet, or aſſeſſe upon the Cuſtome but in manner as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The ſixth Statute is 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Stat.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 1.</note> The King doth grant by way of Charter to the Prelates, Earles, Barons, Commons, Citizens, Burgeſſes and Merchants, that they be not from thenceforth charged nor grieved to make any aide or ſuſtaine charge, if it be not by the common conſent of the Prelates, Earles, Barons, and other great men, and Commons of the Realme, and that in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Statutes grew upon occaſion of an Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſet on Wooll by the King without aſſent of Parliament: Little hath beene objected againſt them, but onely to the firſt, that it was obtained of grace, and not upon inſtance of right, which they gather out of the words of the Law, which are, The Commons pray the King that he would ſtabliſh, that from henceforth no more but the old cuſtome be taken. The like reaſon may be made againſt the King out of the ſame words in the ſame Law: for the King in the ſame Act prayeth the Commons to give him an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon Wools for a time above the old Cuſtome: but the Record of the Petitions exhibited in Parliament, upon which theſe two Lawes are made, cleareth the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</p>
            <p>The firſt was delivered by the Lords in this forme,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Les grands volunt,</hi> that the maletoll ſet on Wools newly, be altogether abated, and that the old cuſtome beheld, and that they may have this in point of Charter, and by inroll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Parliament. This word <hi>(volunt)</hi> had beene too high for a ſuit of grace, and therefore muſt be intended of right. The Commons Petition in forme, is ſomewhat humble, but in effect and purpoſe is rough and ſterne:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 13.</note> the words are theſe, The Commons pray that the maletoll of Wools be taken as it was uſed in ancient time, which is now enhaunced without the aſſent of the Commons, and <hi>(grandes)</hi> as we conceive, and that if it be otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that every one of the Commons may arreſt them without being challenged. According to theſe Petitions,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152499:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>the firſt of theſe two Lawes, is by inrolment in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the ſecond is in forme of a Charter: the firſt doth expreſſe ſome ſpecial commodities: the ſecond doth reach generally at all.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Law directly touching this point,
<note place="margin">14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 2.</note> is that 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. The King doth grant according to the great Charter, that all Merchants denizons, and forrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners may without let ſafely come into the Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land with their goods and Merchandizes, and ſafely tarry, and ſafely returne, paying the Subſidies, cuſtomes and other profits reaſonably due. Upon the words of this Law, was great advantage taken, in this, that beſides cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and Subſidy, which comprehend all the certaine &amp; ordinary duties, the King hath upon the &amp; wares &amp; goods of Merchants, there are other profits ſpoken of to be due: theſe they affirme cannot be underſtood but of Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the King without aſſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer; if they were not duties due to the King beſides, Cuſtome and Subſidie, which might ſatisfie the intention of theſe words, this objection might have had ſome colour in it; but it is plaine that beſides theſe two, there are other profits due to the King upon Merchants goods, as Scavage, Tonage, and the like.</p>
            <p>And you ſhall finde a Petition in Parliament,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 50. <hi>E</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 163.</note> 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3 againſt the raiſing of theſe above the old rate.</p>
            <p>The eight Law is <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>ta.</hi> 5.</note> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2 <hi>ca.</hi> 5. whereby it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted that every Merchant may freely buy and ſell, and paſſe the ſea with their Merchandizes of Wooll and all other things, paying the Cuſtome of old time uſed, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Statute made the laſt Parliament in Midlent, which was the <hi>ſtat.</hi> 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. This Law doth expreſly exclude the novelty of Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>The ninth Law is that 18.
<note place="margin">18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3 <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 3. Whereby it is enacted that the ſea be open to all manner Merchants to paſſe with their Merchandizes where it ſhall pleaſe them.</p>
            <p>The tenth is 27.
<note place="margin">27. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. for the aſſurance of Merchant ſtrangers and other, the King doth will and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152499:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>grant for him &amp; his heires that nothing ſhall be taken over the due Cuſtomes, nor taken of them to his uſe by colour of ſale, or in other manner againſt their wils.</p>
            <p>The eleventh is 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">38 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 2.</note> that all manner Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants aliens and denizens may buy and ſell all manner of Merchandizes, and freely carry them out of the Realm, paying the Cuſtomes and Subſidies thereof due.</p>
            <p>The laſt is 22. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 8.
<note place="margin">22. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 8.</note> by which it was enacted that Tables ſhould be ſet up in ports, by which the certainty and very duty of every cuſtome, toll, and duty or ſumme of money to be demanded and required of wares and Merchandizes ſhall and may plainely appeare and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, to the intent that nothing be exacted otherwiſe then in old time hath beene uſed and accuſtomed.</p>
            <p>By this late Law it appeareth that the judgement of of the whole Parliament was at that time, that nothing was due upon Wares and Merchandizes, but that which was certaine, and had beene anciently due, by which Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are excluded, whoſe qualities are novelty and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, as being ſet on, as preſent occaſion moveth, and proportioned for quantity and other circumſtances, as the will of the King directeth.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Lawes which I conceive moſt directly tend to the reſtraining the Kings of England from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that irregular power of impoſing, at the firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by them to be put in execution, yet not preſſed as their right, and never practiſed but upon oppoſition of the whole State, and at laſt deſerted and given over untill of late, As by that which followeth in the fourth place will appeare.</p>
            <p>My fourth and laſt aſſertion is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cuſtome </seg>4</label> that this practiſeof im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing without aſſent of Parliament, is <hi>contra morem Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorum.</hi> In this I will make an hiſtoricall perluſtration of the times paſt, whereby I will diſcover and make knowne what paſſages have beene in this buſineſſe in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and eſpecially in the high Court of Parliament for the ſpace of 300 yeares and more laſt paſt, ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the raigne of <hi>E.</hi> 1. ſithence which time, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152499:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>not before this Kingdome hath growne into the glory and reputation of foraigne traffique. And as a worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earned Councell, made certaine conſiderations upon this queſtion, framed and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of the greatneſſe of his wit and reaſon: ſo I grounding my ſelfe upon the practiſe of former times, which is the ſafeſt rule where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to ſquare the right both of King and people in this Common wealth, where their right is <hi>jus conſuetudinarium,</hi> a right that groweth by uſe and practiſe, I will propoſe unto you certaine obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of the action and experience of former times un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the raignes of the two late Queenes; by which you may the better ground and frame your judgements in the determination of the right in this queſtion.</p>
            <p>My firſt obſervation is in point of circumſtance, that there never was any Impoſition ſet, but in time of actuall war, and <hi>duplicatis vexillis:</hi> they were ſet on very rarely and ſparingly, but for a ſhort time, and that certaine and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and upon ſome few commodities, and that by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Merchants that were to beare the burthen. In our time the occaſion not ſo ſenſible, the continuance to be perpetuall, the number many hundreds, almoſt no kinde of Commodity ſpared. I will give you ſome few Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of theſe circumſtances ces out of the Records themſelves.</p>
            <p>The maletole of Wooll ſet on by King <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>orig. Scacc. Rent. Theſ.</hi> 22. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>mem. Scac. R. Theſ. T. Mich.</hi>
               </note> 1. which gave the occaſion of the Stat. 25. yeare of his raigne was given by Merchants. The Record ſaith, <hi>Mercatores gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanter conceſſerunt in ſubſidium guerrae Regis,</hi> It further ſheweth, it was for his neceſſity of warre, which then was great alſo.</p>
            <p>For the time of <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 17. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 28.</note> 3. there need not many inſtances, for his whole raigne was almoſt an actuall warfare. As in the ſixt year of his raigne for his warre in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> In the thirteenth year of his raigne for his war in <hi>France,</hi> ſeverall Impoſitions were ſet on.</p>
            <p>In the ſeventeenth yeare of <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Record in the Tower, mentioneth that forty ſhillings Impoſition was upon a ſacke of Wooll by the grant of Merchants,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152499:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>and it was in the time of Warre.</p>
            <p>In the twentieth yeare of King <hi>E.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 20. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 18.</note> it appeareth in the Record, that the Impoſition then put upon Wools, was by the aſſent of Merchants for two yeares, for the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity the King had in his paſſage over the ſea, to recover his right, and to defend the Realme.</p>
            <p>My ſecond obſervation is, never any Impoſition was ſet on by the King out of Parliament, but complaint was made of it in Parliament, and not one that ever ſtood after ſuch complaint made, but remedy was afforded for it, <hi>Et quod Rex inconſultò fecit, conſulto revocavit,</hi> his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power controlled his ſubordinate. In which it is a thing very notable, that the King in no one Caſe, ever claimed, or ſo much as ever named his right or preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, which no doubt would have been done, if it had been thought due, but gave ſatisfaction to the complaint by one of theſe three waies, either by diſcharging them quite and making ſome good Law againſt them. Secondly, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating the people to hold them ſome ſhort time by their favour. Thirdly, by waving his preſent poſſeſſion, and taking that of their gift by Act of Parliament, as an aide which he had ſet on by his abſolute power as an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p>Inſtances of the firſt 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 7. <hi>Rot. part.</hi> 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 36.</note> the Impoſition of Wools taken off, and a Law made againſt it, and the King under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke for him and his ſucceſſors to doe ſo no more: 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3.26.
<note place="margin">38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.45. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.17. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>R.</hi> 18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 1.21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 11. <hi>R. Parl.</hi>
               </note> the Impoſtion of three ſhillings foure pence on a ſacke of Wooll put off upon complaint, and a Law made againſt it, 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 2. the like Statute 45. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. upon a complaint of an Impoſition on Wools made in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, 45. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 42. <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſtances of the ſecond 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 11. a petition upon an Impoſition of 2. s. upon a ſacke of wooll, 2. s. upon a tunne of wine, and ſix pence upon <hi>aver de pois,</hi> all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged preſently, ſaving the two ſhillings upon a ſacke of wooll, and for that intreated that it might ſtay till Eaſter following, and ſo it did, and was then taken away.
<note place="margin">25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 22. <hi>rot. parl.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Inſtance of the third 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 22. the Commons
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152499:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>made petition againſt an impoſition of fourty ſhillings upon a ſacke of wooll granted to the King by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, ſhewing that they ought not to be bound by their act, The King did not claime right or juſtifie, but becauſe his warres were great upon his requeſt had it granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for two yeeres by Act of Parliament, and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no title of Prerogative, neither was it ever ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>My third obſervation is that our Kings have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that it is not their right,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig. in Scau.</hi> 31. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>R. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 1. in his writs he ſent to the officers of his parts to levie three pence on the pound over the old cuſtome, of the Denizons as well as of the Aliens, and to ſuffer the Denizons to enjoy thoſe privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges the Aliens did enjoy by the payment of the encreaſe of Cuſtome, doth give this direction expreſly. That they ſhould not take it of Denizons againſt their will, The words of the Record expreſſe it very fully, <hi>Cum mercato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res extranei &amp; alienigenae pro quibuſdam libertatibus eis per nos conceſſis &amp; priſis nostris quibuſcunqueremiſſis, nobis de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; merchandiſis ſuis quibuſcunque infra regnum &amp; pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem nostram adducend. ultra antiquas custumas dare conceſſerint praeſtationes &amp; custumas ſubſcriptas, viz.</hi> and ſo fetteth downe the increaſes, and amongſt the reſt this three pence upon the pound, and ſo proceedeth, <hi>Ac qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam mercatores de regno nostro &amp; potestate noſtra, ut ipſis dictis libertatibus &amp; immunitatibus uti &amp; gaudere, &amp; quod de priſis nostris quieti eſſe poſſint, praestationes &amp; custumas hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi de bonis &amp; merchandiſis ſuis nobis ſolvere velint, ut acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus, aſſignavimus vos, &amp;c. ad custumas &amp; praestationes praedictas de mercatoribus de regno &amp; potestate nostra colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend. qui eas gratanter &amp; ſine coercione ſolvere voluerint. Ita tamen quod aliquem mercatorem de dicto regno &amp; pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate nostra ad praestationes &amp; custumas hujuſmodi nobis invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſolvend. nullatenus distringatis.</hi> Surely if <hi>E.</hi> 1. had claimed the prerogative of impoſing, hee would never have given theſe cautions in the requiring of that which hee had taken to be his due, as that they ſhould not exact it of any of his ſubjects that were not willing to pay it, nor trouble, nor diſtraine them for it.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152499:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>In the twelfth yeere of <hi>E.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ret. Alem.</hi> 12. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>dorne.</hi> 22. <hi>in turr.</hi>
               </note> wee finde the Record of certaine letters written from the King being then at <hi>Barwick</hi> in the Scottiſh warres, unto the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> in which letters the King ſeemeth to have a great confidence in the devotion of the Archbiſhop, and therefore earneſtly intreateth him to further his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes with his prayers to God, and then addeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Ad hoc pater, cum populus regni nostri variis oneribus, tallagiis &amp; impoſitionibus hactenus praegravetur (quod dolenter referimus) ſed inevitabili neceſſitate compulſi de eiſdem oneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ipſum adhuc relevare non valemus, dictum populum ut tantam neceſſitatem nostram humiliter &amp; benigne patiatur &amp; canitative ſustineat, &amp; priorem (quam penes nos concepit de cetero instanter in orationibus &amp; eleemoſynis ſuis, oneribus praedictis, quae non ex malitia vel preſumptione voluntaria ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum gravant, non obstantibus) exhibeant caritatem, indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiam muncribus &amp; aliis modis, quibus ſecundum Deum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debitis piis exhortationibus inducatis, &amp; nos penes eundem excuſitis, ſperamus namqueſper Dei gratiam, cujus manus cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis indigentibus ſola ſufficiens, &amp; largiflua comprobatur, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiis compenſatius dictum populum viſitare &amp; conſolari pro loco &amp; temporeopportunis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The principall thing I note out of this Record upon the very point of this my third obſervation, is, that the King intending to excuſe himſelfe of the burthens by him laid on the people, and to avoid the blemiſh of wrong and injuſtice in laying thereon, ſaith they were not <hi>onera ex preſumptione voluntaria,</hi> that is, burthens that he preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to lay on at his owne will, whereby hee condemneth impoſitions without aſſent of Parliament, which are <hi>(onera ex voluntate Regis)</hi> to proceed of preſumption, which doth clearly exclude claime of right, and diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the lawfulneſſe of the act. But there are divers other notable paſſages in the Record worthy our marking. As out of the word <hi>(praegravantur)</hi> uſed by the King, wee may gather hee did accompt theſe Impoſitions a grievous burden to his people, which ſheweth his owne pity of them. Hee ſaith further, <hi>Dolentes referimus,</hi> ſhewing his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152499:24"/>griefe and remorſe at it, <hi>&amp; inevitabili neceſſitate compulſi,</hi> hee did it conſtrained by unavoidable neceſſity, ſhewing hee was forced to it againſt his will, by that which viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and breaketh all law, which inferreth, hee would not maintaine his action by law; <hi>Adhuc relevare non valemus;</hi> this inſinuates, hee would eaſe them in good time; <hi>cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem exhiberent,</hi> they ſhould afford him charity in the bearing of them, as if ſo bee in point of juſtice or right they need not, <hi>Penes cundem excuſetis,</hi> the Biſhop ſhould excuſe him to the people, By this he did clearly leave the point of juſtification, and ſo of right: laſtly hee promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth hee would viſite and comfort them <hi>benefic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſativis,</hi> would give them recompence for thoſe ſummes he had ſo raiſed of them; which ſhewed that hee claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them not as due, for then hee needed not give recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for them.</p>
            <p>In the one and twentieth yeere of <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 21. <hi>E</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 16.</note> 3. a petition was exhibited in Parliament, that Levies be not made by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion (ſo they bee in this caſe) nor other things laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people unleſſe they bee granted in Parliament, The Kings anſwer is, If any ſuch impoſitions were made, it was by great neceſſity, and with the aſtent of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Barons, and ſome of the Commons preſent; yet hee will not that ſuch Impoſitions not duly made bee drawne in conſequence. Here the King acknowledgeth an Impoſition not to bee duly made though with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Higher Houſe, and ſome of the Commons, becauſe it was not in full Parliament; much rather hee would have thought ſo, if it had beene by the King alone.</p>
            <p>King <hi>E.</hi> 4. (that was a rough and warlike Prince, and was more beholding to his ſword in the recovery of his right to the Crowne then to the affection of the people) at a Parliament held the ſeventh yeer of his reigne made a Speech to the Commons, Sir <hi>Iohn Say</hi> being then Speaker, in which ſpeech is contained very notable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and very pertinent to our purpoſe; and becauſe the Record is not in print, I will ſet downe the Kings ſpeech <hi>verbatim</hi> as it is entered upon the Parliament roll, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152499:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>then I will make a paraphraſe upon it, <hi>Iohn Say,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 7. <hi>E.</hi> 4. The record begins, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morandum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quod die vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru</hi> 3. <hi>die Parl.</hi>
               </note> and ye Sirs come to this my Court of Parliament for the Commons of this my Realme, The cauſe why I have cald and ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this my preſent Parliament is, that I purpoſe to live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mine owne, and not to charge my ſubjects but in great and urgent cauſes concerning more the Weale of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and alſo the defence of them and of this my Realme, rather than mine owne pleaſure as heretofore by Commons of this Land hath beene done, and borne unto my progenitours in time of need, wherein I truſt that yee Sirs, and all the Commons of this my Land will bee as tender and kinde unto mee in ſuch caſes as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Commons have beene to any of my progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, And for the good will, kindeneſſe, and true hearts that yee have borne, continued, and ſhewed to mee at all times heretofore, I thanke you as heartily as I can: alſo I truſt yee will continue in time comming, for which by the grace of God I ſhall bee to you as good and gracious a King, and reigne as righteouſly upon you as ever did any of my progenitours upon Commons of this my Realme in dayes paſt, and ſhall alſo in time of need apply my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the Weale and defence of you, and of this my Realme, not ſparing my body nor life for any jeopardy that might happen to the ſame.</p>
            <p>Out of this wee may obſerve firſt the Kings Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to live of his owne, and not to charge his ſubjects; by which I gather hee did acknowledge a certain and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct property of that which was his ſubjects from that which was his owne, which excludeth the right to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe at his will, for if that be admitted, the ſubjects pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty is <hi>proprietas pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>caria</hi> not certaine how much of his, is his owne: for that is his which the King will leave him, for there is no limit or reſtraint of the quantity, the right being admitted, but onely the Kings will.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I obſerve is this, that in charging of his ſubjects he would confine himſelfe betweene theſe two bounds; the one, it ſhould bee in great and urgent cauſes concerning more the Weale of them, and the defence of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152499:25"/>them and his Realme, that his owne pleaſure; wherein he condemneth thoſe occaſions, that grew upon exceſſe of private expence by over great bounty, or otherwiſe, and admitteth onely ſuch as grow by reaſon of warres, or other ſuch like publique cauſes concerning the whole State: the other bound or limit is, that thoſe burdens ſhould bee <hi>ſecundum morem majorum,</hi> as heretofore had beene done and borne by the Commons to his anceſtours in time of need. The third thing I obſerve is, that hee acknowledged theſe burdens did proceed out of their good will and kindeneſſe, and not out of his right and prerogative; out of theſe words, that hee truſted they would bee as tender and kinde to him in ſuch caſes as heretofore any Commons had beene to his progenitours: And laſtly, wee may note the recompence promiſed by the King to his ſubjects, for their good wils and kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, his goodneſſe and grace, his juſt and righteous go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; the jeopardy of his body and life for their Weale and defence. Did this King aſſume to himſelfe a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight to lay burdens on his ſubjects at his owne will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their aſſents, that offered to buy them at his need with the price of his blood, the moſt ſacred relique in the Kingdome?</p>
            <p>My fourth obſervation is that in all petitions exhibited by the Commons in Parliament, againſt Impoſitions, the very knot of their griefe, and the principall cauſe of their complaint hath beene expreſſed in thoſe petitions, that the impoſitions have beene without aſſent of Parliament: by which is neceſſarily inferred, that their griefe was in point of right, not of burden.</p>
            <p>In 11.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 11. the complaint of the Impoſition of two ſhilling upon a ſacke of wooll, two ſhillings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a tonne of wine, ſixe pence upon <hi>aver de pois,</hi> the cauſe of grievance expreſſed becauſe it was done <hi>Sans aſſent de Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>25 <hi>E.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Parl.</hi> 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 22.</note> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 22. In a petition the Commons complaine that an impoſition upon wools was ſet by the conſent of the merchants, they pray that Commiſſions bee not made
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152499:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon ſuch ſingular grants, if they bee not in full Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and if any ſuch grants bee made, they may bee held as void.</p>
            <p>17 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 28.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Parl.</hi> 17. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 28.</note> The Commons in their petition informe the King, it is againſt reaſon they ſhould be charged with impoſitions ſet on by aſſent of merchants, and not in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>My fifth obſervation is, that whenſoever any petition was exhibited againſt impoſitions, there was never any reſpect had of the quantity, but they were ever intirely abated, as well where they were ſmall, as where they were great; no requeſt ever made to make them leſſe when they were great, nor excuſe made of their eaſe when they were exceeding ſmall; which ſheweth that it was not the point of burden or exceſſe was reſpected in their complaint, but the point of meere right.</p>
            <p>25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 22.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Parl.</hi> 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 22.</note> Fourty ſhillings ſet an impoſition upon a ſacke of wooll, upon complaint, all taken off, and no ſuit to be eaſed of part, becauſe it was too great.</p>
            <p>36. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 26.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi> 38. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 26.</note> Three ſhillings and four pence upon a ſacke of wooll, all taken off, and no excuſe made for the ſmalneſſe; for 21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 11. two ſhillings a ſacke,
<note place="margin">21. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 11.</note> two ſhillings tonnage, and ſix pence poundage.</p>
            <p>50. <hi>E</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 163.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Parl.</hi> 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>nu.</hi> 163.</note> A great complaint was made in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by the Commons that an impoſition of a peny was ſet upon wools for Tronage over and above the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient due which was but a peny, and ſo the ſubject was charged with two pence. Alſo that a peny was exacted for Meſonage, which was but an halfepeny; which Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Record doth expreſſe did amount to an hundred pounds a yeere. This petty impoſition was as much ſtood upon in point of right, as the other great one of fourty ſhillings, and was taken off upon complaint in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without either juſtification or excuſe for the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it.</p>
            <p>My ſixth obſervation is, that thoſe which have adviſed the ſetting on of impoſitions, without aſſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have beene accuſed in Parliament for giving that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152499:26"/>advice, as of a great offence in the State, and have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſharpe cenſure and great diſgrace by it. Neither doe I finde that the quality of the perſon hath extenuated the blame, as 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>William</hi> L. <hi>Latimer</hi> Chamberlaine to the King, and one of his private Councell was accuſed by the Commons in Parliament of divers deceits and extortions and miſdeeds, and among other things, that hee had procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bee ſet upon wooll, wooll-fells, and other merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes, new impoſitions, to wit, upon a ſacke of wooll elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhillings, which the L. <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imer</hi> ſought to excuſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had the conſent and good liking of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants firſt: But judgement was given againſt him that he ſhould be committed to priſon, be fined and ranſomed at the Kings will, and be put from being of the Councell, and this procuring of impoſitions to bee ſet on without aſſent of Parliament is expreſly ſet downe in the entry of the judgement for one of the cauſes of his cenſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Lyons</hi> a Fermor of the Cuſtomes in <hi>London</hi> the ſame yeere was accuſed in Parliament for the ſame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl</hi> 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> he pleaded, hee did it by the Kings command, and had anſwered the money to the Kings Chamber: yet was condemned and adjudged in Parliament to be committed to priſon, and all his lands and goods were ſeifed into the Kings hand, and at the laſt the hate againſt theſe authours of impoſitions grew ſo that 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. in the ſame Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a petition was exhibited in Parliament to make this a capitall offence; the Record is very ſhort, and therefore I will ſet it downe <hi>verbatim. Item prie le dit Common que foit ordaine per ſtatute en cest preſent parliament de touts ceux qux cy en avant mittont on font pur lour ſinguler profit novels impoſitions per lour authoritie demeſn accrocheants al eux eny ul power de riens que ſoit establi en parliament, ſans aſſent de parliament, que ils eyent judgement de vie &amp; member, &amp; de forisfacture.</hi> To this rough petition the King gave a milde and temperate anſwer, <hi>Courge la Common ley come estoit al avant uſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My ſeventh obſervation is the ceſſation betweene 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. after this cenſure in Parliament, and 4. <hi>Mariae,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152499:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>two hundred yeeres, during which time no King did attempt to impoſe without aſſent of Parliament: and yet we finde in the Parliament rolls, that there was not one of thoſe Kings that raigned in that time, but had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions granted him upon fit occaſion by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon all goods and merchandiles, and at divers times during their Reignes, ſometimes more, ſometimes leſſe upon the tonne and pound, but ever for a time cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and definite; ſo the uſe of them was not given over, but the power of impoſing was ſo clearly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly held to bee in the Parliament, as no King went about to practiſe the contrary.</p>
            <p>But to this ceſſation that was of great weight and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in our evidence, a colour was given by the other ſide to avert the inference made upon it, againſt the Kings right, that is, that during that time, there was ſo great a revenue grew to the Crowne by double Cuſtome paid for all merchandiſes both in <hi>England</hi> and at <hi>Caſtis</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of an Act of Parliament made 8. <hi>H.</hi> 4. which was, that no goods ſhould bee carried out of the Realme but to <hi>Calles,</hi> and by reaſon that the merchants paid Cuſtome both there and here for the ſame goods that in the ſeven and twentieth yeere of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth the Cuſtome of <hi>Callis</hi> was 68000. pounds the yeere: a great ſumme if you conſider the weight of money then, what price it bare, and by reaſon hereof Princes not delighting to charge their munnuting ſubjects but when need is, being ſo amply ſupplied otherwiſe, did not put that prerogative in practice. To this I anſwer, that if that were true that was urged, it might bee ſome probable colour of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of impoſing; but I find it to be quite contrary, and that by Record: for there was no ſuch reſtramt of all commodities not to bee tranſported to any place but <hi>Callis,</hi> but onely wools, wool-fells, leather, tinne, and lead, that were ſtaple wares, which by the ſtature 37. <hi>E.</hi> 3. were to be tranſported thither, and not to any other place, and the ſtaple continued at that place for the moſt part from that time untill long after 27. <hi>H.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. but there was no
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152499:27"/>double Cuſtome paid both here and there by the ſame owner: but the yeerly profits of the Cuſtomes of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lais</hi> at thoſe tiems were ſo farre ſhort of that which hath beene alleaged in 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. that it appeareth in an Act of Parliament 27.
<note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. printed in the booke at large, that the Commons doe complaine that whereas in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Cuſtome of <hi>Callais</hi> was 68000. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> at that time, which was 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. by reaſon of the ill uſage of merchants, it was fallen to bee but 12000. pounds the yeere, ſo then there was great cauſe in that reſpect to have ſet on impoſitions by reaſon of that great abatement of Cuſtomes, and yet it was not then offered to bee done without aſſent of Parliament. But if you looke a little further into the extreme neceſſities of thoſe times, you ſhall finde there never was greater cauſe to have ſtrained prerogatives; for it appeareth in an Act of Parliament 28. <hi>H.</hi> 6. that it was then declared in Parliament by the Chancellour and Treaſurer who demanded reliefe of the people for the King, both for payment of his debts, and for his yeerly livelihood, that the King was then indebted 372000. pounds, which now by the weight of money amounteth to above 1100000. pounds, and that his ordinary expences was more than his yeerly reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue by 19000. pounds yeerly: ſo if ever there was cauſe to put a King to his ſhifts, it was then; yet wee ſee they did not venture to put in practice this ſuppoſed prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative. It further appeareth in that ſtatute that the people among thoſe reaſons they alleaged why they were not able to reteine the King, gave this for one, that they had ſo often granted him tonnage and poundage upon mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes, by which it appeareth hee tooke nothing of merchants by impoſition without grant, for if he had, no doubt they would not have ſtucke to have put him in minde of it. But I pray conſider what became of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Chancellour and Treaſurer: the propoſition had depended in Parliament many yeeres; the effect was, the people intreated the King to reſume all grants he had made from the beginning of his Raigne untill that time,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152499:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>being the twenty eight yeare of his raigne, excepting ſuch as were made upon conſideration valuable, that he might ſo enable himſelfe by that meane by which he had impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed himſelfe and the whole Kingdome: This tooke effect, and the Statute of Reſumptions was thereupon made the ſame yeare, which Record becauſe it is not in print, and declareth theſe things with great gravity and authority: I will ſet downe the very text of it, ſo much as is materiall to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Prayen your Commons in this your preſent Parliament aſſembled to conſider,
<note place="margin">28. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Stat. de Reſump. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turri Lond.</hi> not printed.</note> That where your Chancellor of your Realme of England, your Treaſurer of England, and many other Lords of your Councell, by your high Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your ſaid Commons, at your Parliament holden laſt at Weſtminſter, ſhewed and declared the State of this your Realm, which was, that ye were indebted 372000. l. which is grievous, and that your livelihood in yearely va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue was but 5000. l. And foraſmuch as this 5000. l. to your high and notable State to be kept, and to pay your ſaid debts, will not ſuffice: therefore that your high Eſtate may be relieved. And furthermore it was declared, that your expences neceſſary to your houſhold without al other ordinary charge came to 24000. l. yearely, which exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every yeare in expence neceſſary over your livelihood 19000. l. Alſo pleaſeth it your highneſſe to conſider, that the Commons of your ſaid Realme be as well willing to their power, for the releeving of your Highneſſe, as ever was people to any King of your Progenitors that ever raigned in your ſaid Realme of England: but your ſaid Commons been ſo impoveriſhed, what by taking victuall to your houſhold, and other things in your ſaid Realme, and nought paid for it, and the quinzime by your ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſo often granted, and by the grant of tunnage and poundage, and by the graunt of Subſidie upon Woolls, and other graunts to your Highneſſe, and for lack of execution of juſtice, that your ſaid poore Commons be full nigh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152499:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>and if it ſhould continue longer in ſuch great charge, it could not in any wiſe be had, ne borne: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pleaſeth it your Highneſſe the premiſſes graciouſly to conſider, and that ye by the advice and aſſent of your Lords Spirituall and Temporall, and by the authority of this your preſent Parliament, for the conſideration of your high Eſtate, and in comfort and eaſe of your poore Commons, would take, reſume, ſeiſe and retaine in your hands and poſſeſſion all honours, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This was very plaine dealing by the people with their King, and this is the ſucceſſe of the demaund of ſupply and ſupport had in thoſe daies, being required in point of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, without any recompence or retribution for it. Thus then wee have cleared this point, that betweene 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. and 4. <hi>Mariae,</hi> there was not one impoſition fet without aſſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Queene <hi>Mary</hi> in the fourth yeare of her raigne, upon the wars with France, ſet an Impoſition upon Clothes for this conſideration, that the cuſtome of Woolls was decayed, by reaſon for the moſt paſt they were made into Clothes, which affoorded little cuſtome; for that which in Wooll, paid for cuſtome and ſubſidie 40. s. made into Cloath paid but 4. s. 4. d. To recompence this by an indifferent equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, there was ſet upon a Cloath 5. s. 6. d. which impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did not make up the loſſe ſuſtained in the cuſtome of Wooll, by 13. s. 4. d. in 40. s. This was <hi>Iuſtum,</hi> but not <hi>Iuſtè.</hi> This religious Prince invironed with infinite trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the Church and Common-wealth, and much impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed by her devotion, in renouncing the profits of the Church lands that were in the Crowne by the ſuppreſſion, was the firſt that made digreſſion from the ſteps of her worthy Progenitors, in putting on that impoſition without aſſent of Paſliament; for that very conſideration of the loſſe of cuſtome, by turning of Wooll to Clothing, came into treatie in the 24. yeare of <hi>E.</hi> 3. when the art of clothing began firſt to be much practiſed in this Kingdome, and then
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152499:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the recompence of the loſſe ſo ſuſtained in the decay of cuſtome of Woolls, there was ſet upon a Cloath by act of Parliament above the olde cuſtome, 14. d. for a Denizen, and for an Alien, 21. d. This is recited in a Record in the Exchequer, 48. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>rot.</hi> 2. <hi>R. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> origin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orig. in Scacc.</hi> 48. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Ro.</hi> 2. <hi>R. Theſ.</hi> 1. <hi>El. Dyer ſo.</hi> 165.</note> But I pray you examine how this impoſition of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was digeſted by the people. We ſee in the Caſe in my Lord <hi>Dier</hi> 1. <hi>Eli. fo.</hi> 165. that the Merchant found great griefe at it, and made exclamation and ſuit to <hi>Q. Eliz.</hi> to be unburdened of it: The very reaſon of their griefe expreſſed in that caſe is, becauſe it was not ſet on by Parliament, but by the Queenes abſolute power; So that was the ground of that complaint, the very point of right.</p>
            <p>This cauſe was referred to all the Judges, to report whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Queene might ſet on this impoſition without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Pailiament: They divers times had conference about it, but have not yet made report for the King, which is an infallible preſumption, that their opinions were not for him; for it is a certain rule among us, that if a queſtion concerning the Kings prerogative, or his profit be referred to the Judges, if their opinions be for the King, it will bee ſpeedily publiſhed, and it were indiſcretion to conceale it; but if there be no publication, then we make no doubt, but that their opinions are either againſt the King, or at leaſt they ſtick, and give none for him.</p>
            <p>The ſame Queene <hi>Mary</hi> upon reſtraint of bringing in of French commodities occaſioned by the then wars with France, ſet an impoſition upon Gaſcoigne Wines, which continueth yet: So the kingdome of England by the injuſtice of that Prince was clogged with thoſe two heavy impoſitions contrary to the right of the Kingdome, and the acts of her Progenitors.</p>
            <p>Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſet on that upon ſweet Wines, which grew alſo upon the occaſion of the troubles with Spaine. That upon Allome was none, it was rather a Monopolie to Maſter <hi>Smith</hi> the Cuſtomer of London, for the ingroſſing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152499:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>of all Allomes into his owne hands, for which priviledge he gave a voluntary impoſition upon that commodity: It was like the priviledge granted to <hi>Iohn Pechey</hi> of the ſweet Wines by <hi>E.</hi> 3. for which the Patentee was called into the Parliament houſe, 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. and was there puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his Patent taken away and cancelled.</p>
            <p>What impoſitions have been ſet on in the Kings time, I need not expreſſe, they are ſet downe particularly in the booke of rates that is in print, they are not eaſily numbered: the time for which they are raiſed is not ſhort, the Patent prefixed to that booke bearing date 28. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uln</hi> 6. <hi>Iacobi</hi> will inſtruct you ſufficiently in that point; they be limited to the King, his heires and ſucceſſors: which I ſuppoſe is the firſt eſtate of Fee ſimple of impoſitions that ever man read of.</p>
            <p>My eighth and laſt obſervation is upon tunnage and poundage given to the King of this Realme, upon Wares and Merchandizes exported and imported, which is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition by act of Parliament, and as it will appeare, was given out of the peoples good will, as a very gratification to the King, to enjoyne him thereby from the deſire of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary impoſitions, and to conclude him by that gift in Parliament from attempting to take any other without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament, for after the ceaſing of voluntary impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, theſe Parliamentary ones were frequent in the times of the King that ſucceeded, but they were never gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but for yeares, with expreſſe caution how the money ſtrould be beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owed, As towards the defence of the Seas, protection of traffique, or ſome ſuch other publique cauſes: ſometimes ſpeciall ſequeſtrators made by the act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by whoſe hands the money ſhould be delivered, As 5.
<note place="margin">5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2 <hi>n.</hi> 13.10. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 12. 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. in a printed Statute. The rates that were given were very variable, ſometimes ii. s. tunnage and vi. d. poundage, as 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2. iii. s. tunnage, and xii. d. poundage, 10. <hi>R.</hi> 2. which grants were not to endure the longeſt of them above a yeare, xviii. d. tunnage, vi. d. poundage, in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152499:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>17. <hi>R.</hi> 2. iii. s. tunnage, and xii. d. poundage granted to <hi>H.</hi> 4. in the thirteenth yeare of his raigne for a certaine time, in which Statute there is this clauſe, That this aide in time to come ſhould not be taken an example to charge the Lords and Commons in manner of Subſidie, unleſſe it be by the wills of the Lords and Commons, and that by a new grant to be made in full Parliament in time to come. This clauſe in good and proper conſtruction may be taken to be a very convention betweene the King and his people in Parliament, that he ſhould not from thenceforth, nor any of his Succeſſors ſet on impoſitions without aſſent of Parliament. The like impoſition was granted to <hi>H.</hi> 5.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 1. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 17.</note> in the firſt yeare of his raigne for a ſhort time towards the defence of the Realme, and ſafeguard of the Sea upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition expreſſed in the act, that the Merchants Denizens, and eſtrangers comming into the Realme with their Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes, ſhould be well and honeſtly uſed and handled, paying the ſaid Subſidie as in the time of his Father, and his noble Progenitors Kings of England without oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or extortion: In the end of which act the Commons proteſted, being bound by any grant in time to come, for the purpoſes aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H.</hi> 6. in the one and thirtieth yeare of his raigne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 31. <hi>H</hi> 6. 12. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. 6. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Ma. c.</hi> 18. 1. <hi>El. c.</hi> 19. 1. <hi>Iac. c.</hi> 33.</note> had tunnage and poundage given him for his life. <hi>E.</hi> 4. had it given him the third yeare of his raigne, as it appeareth in a Statute 12. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. in the ſixth yeare of his raigne, and all ſince in the firſt yeare of their raignes have had it given them for terme of their life, and being now ſo certainly ſetled in it, do reach further at that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they are in conſcience and honour excluded by this voluntarie gratification: For can any man give me a reaſon, why the people ſhould give this impoſition of tunnage and poundage above the due cuſtome upon all commodities, if the King by his prerogative might ſet on impoſitions without aſſent of Parliament; and were not that a wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e action in a King, to take that of his people as a benevolence
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152499:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>from them, with limitation of the ſame, and in what it ſhould be imployed, and how they will be uſed for it, and for what time he ſhall have it, which he might juſtly take without their conſents, unclogged of theſe unpleaſing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combrances.</p>
            <p>The Statute of tunnage and poundage made in our times that are altogether inclined to flattery, doe yet retaine in them certain ſhewes and rumors of thoſe ancient liberties, although indeed the ſubſtance be loſt, as in the Srat. 1. <hi>lac. cap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iac. c.</hi> 33.</note> 33. we declare that we truſt, and have ſure confidence of his Majeſties good will towards us, in and for the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſure defending of the Seas, and that it will pleaſe his highneſſe, that all Merchants, as well Denizens as Strangers comming into this Realme, be well and honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreated and demeaned for ſuch things whereof Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is granted, as they were in the time of the Kings Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors and Predeceſſors without oppreſſion to them to be done. By this clauſe as it now continueth, the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of this Statute appeareth to be, that there ought no other impoſition be laid upon Merchants beſides theſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by this Statute, and this intention hath been well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by uſe and practiſe from the time of <hi>E.</hi> 3. to the time of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> as before is declared.</p>
            <p>Thus much of this laſt reaſon made from obſervation, and the action of our Nation. I will anſwer now ſuch maine objections as have been made againſt the peoples right, and have not been touched by me <hi>obiter</hi> in my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>That which hath been moſt inſiſted upon is this, that the King by his prerogative Royall hath the cuſtodie of the Havens and Ports of this Iſland, being the very gates of this Kingdome; that he in his royall function and office is only truſted with the keyes of theſe gates; that he alone hath power to ſhut them, and to open them when, and to whom he in his Princely wiſdome ſhall ſee good: that by the Law of England he may reſtraine the perſons of any
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152499:30"/>from going out of the Land, or from comming into it: That he may of his owne power and diſcretion prohibite exportation and importation of goods and merchandizes; and out of this prerogative and preheminence, the power of impoſing, as being derivative, doth ariſe and reſult, For <hi>Cui quod maius eſt, licet, &amp; ei quod eſt minus licitum eſt:</hi> So their reaſon briefly is this, the King may reſtraine the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the perſon, and of the goods; therefore he may ſuffer them not to paſſe, but <hi>ſub modo,</hi> paying ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition for his ſufferance as he ſhall ſet upon them: for the grounds and propoſitions laid in this objection, I ſhall not be much againſt any one of them; others of them muſt be qualified ere they be confeſſed, but the inference and argument made upon them, I utterly deny; for in it there is <hi>mutatio hypotheſis,</hi> and a tranſition from a thing of one nature, to a thing of another; As the premiſſes are of a power in the King only fiduciary, and in point of truſt and government, the concluſion inferres a right of intereſt and gaine; Admit the King hath <hi>Cuſtodiam portuum,</hi> yet hee hath but the cuſtody, which is truſt, and not <hi>Dominium utile;</hi> He hath power to open and ſhut upon conſideration of publike good to the people and State, but not to make gaine and benefit by it: The one is protection, the other is expilation.
<note place="margin">Portus ſunt Publici.</note> The Ports in their owne nature are publike free for all to goe in and out, yet for the common good, this liberty is reſtrainable by the wiſdome and policy of the Prince, who is put in truſt to diſcerne the times when this naturall liberty ſhall be reſtrained. In 1. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>fo.</hi> 10.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>H.</hi> 7.10</note> in the caſe of the Horentines for their Allome, the Lord chiefe Juſtice <hi>Huſſey</hi> doth write a Caſe, that in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 4. a Legate from the Pope being at Calice to come into England, it was reſolved in full Councell (as the booke ſaith) before the Lords and Judges that he ſhould not have licence to come into England un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe he would take an oath at Calice, that he would bring nothing with him that ſhould be prejudiciall to the King and his Crowne.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152499:31"/>
            <p>The King by the Common Law may ſend his Writ, <hi>Ne exeas regnum</hi> to any ſubject of the Realme, but the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Writ is, <hi>Quia datum est nobis intelligi, quod tu verſus partes exteras abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> licentia noſtra clam deſtinas te di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertere, &amp; quamplurima nobis &amp; coronae noſtrae preiudicia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fitzh. N. B.</hi> 85. <hi>b.</hi>
               </note> Fitzh. N. B. 85. b. So in point of government, and Common good of the Realme, he may reſtraine the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: but to conclude, therefore he may take money; not to reſtraine, is to ſell government, truſt, and common juſtice, and moſt unworthy the divine office of a King. But let us compare this power of the King in forraigne affaires, with the like power he hath in Domeſtique government. There is no queſtion but that the King hath the cuſtodie of the gates of all the Townes and Cities in England, as well as all the Ports and Havens, and upon conſideration of the Weal publike may open and ſhut them at his pleaſure, As if the infection of the ſickneſſe be dangerous in places vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine to the City of London, the King may command that none from thoſe places ſhall come into the City: May he therefore ſet an impoſition upon thoſe that he ſuffereth to come into the City? So, if by reaſon of infection he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the bringing of Wares, and Merchandizes from ſome Cities or Townes in this Kingdome to any great Faire or Mart, Shall he therefore reſtraine the bringing of Goods thither unleſſe money be given him by way of impoſition?</p>
            <p>The King in his diſcretion in point of equity, and for qualifying the rigour of the Law, may enjoyne any of his Subjects by his Chauncellor from ſuing in his Court of Common Law: May he therefore make a benefit by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining all from ſuit in his Courts, unleſſe they pay him an impoſition upon their ſuits?
<note place="margin">2. <hi>E.</hi> 3.7.</note> In 2. <hi>E.</hi> 3. in the caſe of the Earle of Richmond before cited, the King had granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the men of great Yarmouth, that all the Ships that arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the Port of Yarmouth, which conſiſted of three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verail Ports, great Yarmouth, little Yarmouth, and Gerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton ſhould arrive all at great Yarmouth, and at no other
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152499:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>place within that Port. The lawfulneſſe of this Patent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in queſtion in the Kings Court, it was reaſoned in the Kings behalfe for the upholding of the graunt, as it is now, that the King had the cuſtodie of the Port, he might reſtrain Merchants from landing at all in his Kingdome: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of the ſame power might appoint where, and in what Haven they ſhould land, and in no other; This Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was demurred on in the Kings Bench, as being grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Law, but the Caſe depending was adjourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Parliament for the weight and conſequence of it, and there the Patent was condemned,
<note place="margin">9. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> and a Law made againſt ſuch, and the like graunts.</p>
            <p>The Preſidents that were vouched for maintenance of this power of reſtraint in the King, were foure, produced almoſt in ſo many hundred yeares,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. parl.</hi> 2. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 16. <hi>Rot. fin.</hi> 2. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 17. <hi>Rot. clauſ.</hi> 10. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>dor.</hi> 31. <hi>Rot. clauſ.</hi> 17. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>in dorſ.</hi>
               </note> whereof two were in the ſecond yeare of <hi>E.</hi> 1. one in the tenth yeare of <hi>E.</hi> 3. another in the ſeventeenth yeere of <hi>H.</hi> 6. ſince which time wee heare of none but by Act of Parliament, as they had beene uſually and regularly before. To theſe I will give anſwer, out of themſelves, out of the common law, out of divers ſtatutes, and out of the practiſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. The reſtraint in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 1. the one of them was to forbid the carrying of wooll out of the Realme, the other was to forbid all Traffique with the Flemings. That of 10. <hi>E.</hi> 3. was to reſtraine the expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſhip-timber out of the Realme. That of 17. <hi>H.</hi> 6. to prohibite Traffique with the ſubjects of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi> Theſe preſidents are rare, yet they have in them inducements out of publique reſpects to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; for the rule of Common law in this caſe, I take it to bee as the reverend Judge Sir <hi>Anthony Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert</hi> holds it in his writ of <hi>Ne exeas regnum in Na. Br.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fitzh. N. B.</hi> 85.</note> that by the Common law any man may goe out of the Kingdome, but the King may upon cauſes touching the good of the Common-wealth reſtraine any man from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by his Writ or Proclamation, and if hee then goe, it is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152499:32"/>a contempt. This opinion of his is confirmed by the booke,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dier.</hi> 1. <hi>El.</hi> 165. <hi>Dier.</hi> 13. <hi>El.</hi> 296.</note> 1. <hi>Eliz. fol.</hi> 165. <hi>Dier.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>Etiz. Dier.</hi> 296. In like manner if a ſubject of <hi>England</hi> be beyond ſea, and the King ſend to him to repaire home, if hee doe it not, his lands and goods ſhall bee ſeiſed for the contempt, and this was the caſe of <hi>William de Brittain</hi> E. of <hi>Richmond.</hi> 19. <hi>E.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">19. <hi>E.</hi> 2.</note> Hee was ſent by the King into <hi>Gaſcoine</hi> on a meſſage, and refuſed to returne, for which contempt his goods, chattels, lands, and tenements were ſeiſed into the Kings hands:
<note place="margin">2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>P. &amp; M. Dier.</hi> 128.</note> the Record is cited, 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Ph. &amp; M.</hi> in my <hi>L. Dier. fol.</hi> 128. <hi>B.</hi> and the law there held to bee ſo at that time upon a queſtion moved in the Queenes behalfe againſt divers that being beyond the ſeas refuſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne upon commandment ſent unto them to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: the ſame is againe for law confirmed in the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of <hi>Suffolke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dier.</hi> 2. <hi>El.</hi> 176.5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> caſe 2. <hi>Eliz. Dier.</hi> 176. but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law was altered in this point by the ſtatute of 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. by which the paſſage of all people is defended that they may not goe without licence except the Lords and other great men of the Realme, merchants, and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: ſo for the merchants which are the people dealt withall in the buſineſſe in hand, the Common law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth as it was before the ſtatute, and ſo it was held, 12.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dier.</hi> 12. <hi>El.</hi> 196.</note> 
               <hi>El. Dier.</hi> 196. where the caſe was, An Engliſh mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant being a Papiſt went over ſea, and being there, did ſettle himſelfe to remaine there for enjoying the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his conſcience: it was moved here in <hi>England,</hi> that his going without licence ſhould bee a contempt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee went not to traffique as a merchant, but for the cauſe of Religion: it was reſolved, no ſuch averment would be taken in this caſe, for that the very calling and vocation of being a merchant did give him liberty to goe out of the Kingdome when hee would, and therefore the ſecret intent of his going was not to bee enquired after, <hi>Sed lex inspicit quod vertſimilius.</hi> Therefore it was in this caſe held no contempt, but at this day the law is as it was
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152499:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>before, 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2 <hi>cap</hi> 2. for that ſtatute is repealed 4. <hi>Iac.
<note place="margin">4. <hi>Iac. cap.</hi> 1.</note> cap.</hi> 1. And all men whatſoever are now at liberty by the Common law to paſſe out of the Realme. There is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt this inconvenient liberty a Proclamation dated at <hi>Westminster.</hi> 9. <hi>Iul.</hi> 5. <hi>Iac.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proclamati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 9. <hi>lul.</hi> 5. <hi>Iac.</hi>
               </note> To the very ſame effect in point of reſtraint of paſſage with the ſtatute of <hi>R.</hi> 2. So the ſubject is in this much the more at eaſe and liberty than he was before: that his going over ſea without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence doth not induce any forfeiture, but onely incurreth the cenſure of a contempt, and therefore it were to bee wiſhed that ſome firme law might bee made in the caſe both for the execution of ſo good a point of policy, and for the more quiet of the State, in knowing the certainty of the puniſhment for the offence.</p>
            <p>This liberty and freedom of merchants hath been ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened and confirmed by many notable lawes before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.15. <hi>E.</hi> 3 <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. 18. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 1. <hi>c:</hi> 3.</note> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other, and therefore though it bee admitted that the King may reſtraine perſons and goods, yet it may well bee denied, that he hath power of himſelf alone without aſſent of Parliament ſimply and indefinitely to reſtraine all traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique in generall, or to ſhut up all the havens and ports, and to barre the vent and iſſuing of wares and merchandiſes of the whole Kingdome, as appeareth plainely that this hath been done this three hundred yeersor near thereabouts by Act of Parliament onely, and that the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> made this matter of Traffique ſo tender a caſe to deale in, as that it hath ever held it a matter fit for the conſultation of the great Councell of the Kingdome, and for no other.</p>
            <p>In 11. <hi>E.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">11. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> the exportation of wools was prohibited by Act of Parliament, in which ſtatute there was this clauſe, untill that by the King and his Councell it bee thereof otherwiſe provided: which power ſo given to the King to be uſed for the good of the Common-wealth gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to him to abuſe it to his profit and commodity by giving licences of tranſportation to all that would give
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152499:33"/>fourty ſhillings upon a ſacke of wooll above the due Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. This appeareth in the Records in the Exchequer, 13.
<note place="margin">13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>R. Theſ. rot.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 2. <hi>Ram. Theſ.</hi> I will deſcribe the Record that you may perceive the ground of it the better, <hi>Rex colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoribus Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tumae in portum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnae Iermouth ſalutem. Quia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſimus dilecto &amp; fidel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nostro Hugoni de Wriothſley, quod ipſe viginti &amp; ſaptem ſaccos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anae &amp; demid. de lanis ſuis propriis in portu prae dicto cariare &amp; eas uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Antwerpe ad ſtapulam noſtram ibidem ducere poſſit, ſolvendo ibidem dilecto clerico nostro Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmo de Northwell custodi guarderobae nostrae</hi> 40. s. <hi>pro quoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet ſaoco pro custuma &amp; ſubſidio inde nobis debitis, &amp;c. vobis mandamus quod praedict. Hugon. dictos viginti ſeptem ſaccos lanae &amp; dimid. in portu praedicto cartare permittatis, &amp;c.</hi> And another the ſame yeere.
<note place="margin">13. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>rot.</hi> 12. <hi>R. Theſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rex collectoribus custumae, &amp;c. Cum nuper ordinaverimus quod paſſagium lanarum, &amp;c. aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum existeret, &amp; quod ſigillum nostrum quod dicitur Coket, quod prius claudi &amp; ſub ſerra custod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> mandavimus ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riretur, &amp; apertum teneretur, ideo vobis mandavimus quod ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillum praedictum in portu praedicto aperiri, &amp; apertum teneri faciatis, &amp; omnes illos qui hujuſmodi lanas cariare &amp; ducere velint permittatis, receptis prius ab iiſdem. viz. de mercatoribus &amp; aliis indigenis</hi> 40. s. <hi>de quolibet ſaeco <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anae.</hi> Divers other ſuch ſales of traffique occaſioned by this parliamentary reſtraint were made betweene 11.
<note place="margin">14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. that the reſtraint was made, and 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that this inconvenience being eſpied, the ſea was opened by ſtatute, and the reſtraint re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved 14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. 15 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>ſtar.</hi> 2. And this fourty ſhillings ſo exacted was complained of, as an impoſition in Parliament, and the occaſion and the effect were both taken away together by Act of Parliament, 14.
<note place="margin">14. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ce.</hi> 21. <hi>ſt.</hi> 1. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp; ſtat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>It followed in all Kings times ſithence the death of <hi>E.</hi> 3. that this opening and ſhutting of the havens, reſtraining and enlarging of traffique was done by Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>I will give one inſtance in the Raigne of every King,
<note place="margin">5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2.</note> 5. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. For the paſſage of wooll, wool-fells, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152499:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>leather, 6. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.
<note place="margin">6. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>ſt.</hi> 2.</note> For the traffique and commerce with merchants aliens, 2. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſtat.</hi> 2. For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of ſtaple commodities to places certaine, and for the traffique of the merchants of the weſt, 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> that is enacted in Parliament which is contained in the Proclamation, 17. <hi>H</hi> 6. cited for a preſident, that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> made an ordinance whereby the traffique of the Engliſh Nation was reſtrained, that therefore the Engliſhmen ſhould not traffique with the ſubjects of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. 19. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> The ſame thing enacted upon the like occaſion 4. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1.19. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 21. the importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of divers commodities forbidden as being prejudiciall to the manufactures within the Realme. 6. <hi>H.</hi> 8 <hi>cap</hi> 12.
<note place="margin">6. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> The exportation of <hi>Norfolk</hi> woolls out of the Realme forbidden. 26. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.
<note place="margin">26. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 10.</note> Power is given to the King to order and diſpoſe of the traffique of merchants at his pleaſure, and the reaſon is given, becauſe otherwiſe the leagues and amities with forreigne Princes might bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached by reaſon of reſtraint made by divers ſtatutes then ſtanding on foote, whereby it appeareth that it was not then taken to bee law, that the King had an abſolute power in himſelfe to order and diſpoſe of the courſe of traffique without helpe of a ſtatute. 2. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>P. &amp; M. c.</hi> 5.</note> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of leather reſtrained. 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>Ph. &amp; Ma.</hi> The exportation of herring, butter, cheeſe, and other victuals forbidden. 18. <hi>Eliza. cap.</hi> 8. the exportation of tallow,
<note place="margin">18. <hi>El. cap.</hi> 8.</note> raw hides, leather. So in all times no uſe of Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in matters of this nature, but Acts of Parliament ſtill procured: wherefore in mine opinion it behoveth them that doe ſo earneſtly urge this argument, (the King may reſtraine traffique, therefore may impoſe,) to prove better then they have done, that the King may reſtraine traffique of his owne abſolute power: for as the naturall policy and conſtitution of our Common-wealth is, wee may better ſay, that is law which is <hi>de more gentis,</hi> then that which floweth from the reaſon of any man guided by his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152499:34"/>generall notion and apprehenſion of power regall <hi>in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere</hi> not <hi>in individuo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt aſſault made againſt this right of the Kingdome was an objection grounded upon policy, and matter of State, as that it may ſo fall out that an impoſition may beſet by a forreigne Prince that may wring our people, in which caſe the counterpoiſe is, to ſet on the like here upon the ſubjects of that Prince, which policy if it be not ſpeedily executed, but ſtayed untill a Parliament, may in the meane time prove vaine and idle, and much damage may bee ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained that cannot afterwards be remedied.</p>
            <p>This ſtraine of policy maketh nothing to the point of right; our rule is in this plaine Common-wealth of ours, <hi>Oportet neminem eſſe ſapientiorem legibus:</hi> if there bee an inconvenience, it is fitter to have it removed by a lawfull meanes, than by an unlawfull: but this is rather a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe than an inconvenience, that is a prejudice in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſome few, but not hurtfull to the Common-wealth: and it is more tolerable to ſuffer an hurt to ſome few for a ſhort time, than to give way to the breach and violation of the right of the whole Nation: for that is the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, neither need it bee ſo difficult or tedious to have the conſent of the Parliament, if they were held as they ought, or might be; but our ſureſt guide in this will bee the example of our anceſtours in this very caſe, and that in the time of one of the moſt politique Princes that ever reigned in this Kingdome.
<note place="margin">7. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> 7. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. You ſhall finde an Act of Parliament, in which it was recited that the Venetians had ſet upon the Engliſh merchants that laded Malmeſeyes at <hi>Candy</hi> foure duckets of gold upon a But, which in ſterling was eighteene ſhillings the But. It was therefore enacted that every merchant ſtranger that brought Malmeſey into this Kingdome ſhould pay eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene ſhillings the But over and above the due Cuſtome uſed, this impoſition to indure untill they of <hi>Venice</hi> had ſet aſide that of foure duckats the But upon the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:152499:34"/>
            <p>Much hath beene learnedly uttered upon this argument in the maintenance of the peoples right, and in anſwering that which hath beene preſſed on the contrary, but my meaning is not to expreſſe in this diſcourſe all that hath or may bee ſaid on either ſide, but onely to make a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance ſomewhat larger of that which I my ſelfe offered as my <hi>ſymbolum</hi> towards the making up of this great rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of the Common-wealth, which if it bee not well audited, may in time coſt the ſubjects of <hi>England</hi> very deare. My hope is of others that laboured very worthily in this buſineſſe, that they will not ſuffer their paines to die, and therefore I have forborne to enter into their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. I will end with that ſaying of that true and honeſt Counſellour <hi>Philip Comines</hi> in his 5th. booke the 18. chap. <hi>That it is more honourable for a King to ſay,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ph. Comines l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> I have ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and obedient ſubjects, that they deny me nothing I demand, than to ſay, I levie what me list, and I have priviledges ſo to doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:152499:35"/>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:152499:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>After the Kings right to impoſe had beene thorowly examined in Parliament, and there determined not to be in him alone, without aſſent of Parliament, among other Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of grievance given unto his Majeſtie, this hereafter was concerning impoſitions.</head>
               <p>THE policie and conſtitution of this your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties kingdome appropriates unto the Kings of this Realme, with aſſent of Parliament, as well the ſoveraigne power of making Lawes, as that of raxing or impoſing upon the ſubjects goods or merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, wherein they juſtly have ſuch a propriety, as may not without their conſent be altered or changed: This is the cauſe that the people of this kingdome, as they have ever ſhewed themſelves faithfull and loving to their Kings, and ready to aide them in all their juſt occaſions, with voluntary contributions: ſo have they been ever carefull to preſerve their owne liberties and rights when any thing hath been done to prejudice or impeach the ſame: And therefore when their Princes, either occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by war, or by their over great bounty, or by any other neceſſity, have without conſent of Parliament ſet on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſitions either within the Land, or upon commodities exported or imported by the Merchants, they have in open Parliament complained of it, in that it was done without
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152499:36"/>their conſents, and thereupon never failed to obtaine a ſpeedy and full redreſſe without any claime made by the Kings, of any power or prerogative in that point. And though the Law of propriety be originall and carefully preſerved by the common Lawes of this Realme, which are as ancient as the Kingdome it ſelfe, yet thoſe famous Kings for the better contentment and aſſurance of their loving ſubjects agreed that this olde fundamentall right ſhould be further declared and eſtabliſhed by act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein it is provided that no ſuch charge ſhould ever be laid upon the people without their common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, as may appeare by ſundry Records of former times.</p>
               <p>We therefore your Majeſties moſt humble Commons aſſembled in Parliament, following the example of this worthy care of our anceſtors, and out of our duty to thoſe for whom we ſerve, finding that your Majeſtie without advice and conſent of your lords and Commons, hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in time of peace ſet both greater impoſitions, and farre more in number then any your noble anceſtors did ever in time of Warre, doe with all humility preſent this moſt juſt and neceſſary petition unto your Majeſtie, that all impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſet without aſſent of Parliament, may be quite abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and taken away, And that your Majeſtie likewiſe in imitation of your royall progenitors will be pleaſed, that a Law in your time, and during this Seſſion of Parliament may be alſo made to declare that all impoſitions of any kinde ſet, or to be ſet upon your people, their goods or merchandizes, ſave only by common conſent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are, and ſhall be voide: Wherein your Majeſty ſhall not only give your ſubjects great ſatisfaction in point of their right, but alſo bring exceeding joy and comfort to them who now ſuffer, partly through the abating of the price of native commodities, and partly through the raiſing of all forraigne, to the overthrow of Merchants and Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, the cauſing of a generall dearth, and decay of all wealth among your people, who will be thereby no leſſe diſcouraged then diſabled to ſupply your Majeſtie when occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:152499:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>20. Maii, 1641.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>AT a Committee appointed by the honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe of Commons, for examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Bookes, and of the licencing and ſuppreſsing of them, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is ordered that this Treatiſe be publiſhed in Print, unleſſe the Licencer ſhall ſhew good cauſe to the contrary,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>EDVVARD DERING.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152499:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
